你好
Hello.
我叫弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
My name's Forrest. Forrest Gump.
你想吃一块巧克力吗
Do you want a chocolate?
我可以吃下150万块这东西
I could eat about a million and a half of these.
我妈妈总是说
My mama always said
生活就像一盒巧克力
life was like a box of chocolates.
你永远不知道你将得到什么
You never know what you're gonna get.
你这双鞋一定很舒服
Those must be comfortable shoes.
我猜穿着这种鞋
I'll bet you could walk all day
走一整天都不会累
in shoes like that and not feel a thing.
我也想要那样的鞋
I wish I had shoes like that.
我的脚很疼
My feet hurt.
妈妈总是说
Mama always said
你可以通过鞋来了解一个人的很多方面
there's an awful lot you could tell about a person by their shoes:
他们要去哪儿  他们去过哪儿
where they're going, where they've been.
我穿坏过很多双鞋
I've worn lots of shoes.
我猜如果我仔细想想
I bet if I think about it real hard,
就能想起我的第一双鞋
I could remember my first pair of shoes.
妈妈说它们能带我去任何地方
Mama said they'd take me anywhere.
她说它们是我的魔法鞋子
She said they was my magic shoes.
好了  弗里斯特  你可以睁开眼睛了
All right, Forrest, you can open your eyes now.
走一走试试看
Let's take a little walk around.
感觉怎么样
How do those feel?
他的腿很强壮  甘夫人
His legs are strong, Mrs. Gump,
是我见过最强壮的
as strong as I've ever seen,
但是他的脊背像政客一样扭曲
but his back is as crooked as a politician.
不过我们会把他扳直的  对吧  弗里斯特
But we're gonna straighten him right up, now, aren't we, Forrest?
弗里斯特
Forrest!
我还是婴儿的时候
Now, when I was a baby,
妈妈用南北战争时期伟大的英雄
Mama named me after the great Civil War hero,
内森·弗里斯特将军的名字给我取了名
General Nathan Bedford Forrest.
她说我们和他有什么亲缘关系
She said we was related to him in some way.
他做过的事情是
And what he did was,
他创建了一个叫三K党的俱乐部
he started up this club called the Ku Klux Klan.
他们都披着长袍和床单
They'd all dress up in their robes and their bed sheets
表现得像鬼魂或幽灵之类的
and act like a bunch of ghosts or spooks or something.
他们甚至给马披上床单  骑着到处跑
They'd even put bed sheets on their horses and ride around.
不管怎样  我的名字就是这么来的
And anyway, that's how I got my name,
弗里斯特·甘
Forrest Gump.
妈妈说"弗里斯特"这个名字
Mama said that the "Forrest" part
是用来提醒我  有时候我们都会做
was to remind me that sometimes we all do things that,
没有道理的事
well, just don't make no sense.
好了  出来  出来
Okay... Get it, get it...
等等  是这边吗  等一下
Wait, is it this way? Hold on.
好了
All right...
你们看什么看
What are you all staring at?
你们没见过腿上
Haven't you ever seen a little boy
装着支架的小男孩吗
with braces on his legs before?
别让任何人告诉你他们高你一等  弗里斯特
Don't ever let anybody tell you they're better than you, Forrest.
如果上帝希望每个人都是一样的
If God intended everybody to be the same,
他就会让我们的腿上都装着支架
he'd have given us all braces on our legs.
妈妈总是有办法把事情解释得
Mama always had a way of explaining things
让我也能听懂
so I could understand them.
我们住在离17号公路四百米远的地方
We lived about a quarter mile off Route 17,
离阿拉巴马州绿弓镇大约八百米
about a half mile from the town of Greenbow, Alabama.
那地方隶属绿弓县
That's in the county of Greenbow.
自从大约一千年前我妈妈的
Our house had been in Mama's family
爷爷的爷爷的爷爷漂洋过海来到这里
since her grandpa's grandpa's grandpa
这栋房子就一直是我妈妈家的
had come across the ocean about 1,000 years ago,
差不多是这样
something like that.
由于家里只有我和妈妈
Since it was just me and Mama
而我们又有那么多空房间
and we had all these empty rooms,
妈妈决定把那些房间租出去
Mama decided to let those rooms out,
主要是租给过路人
mostly to people passing through,
他们来自莫比尔  蒙哥马利之类的地方
like from, oh, Mobile, Montgomery, places like that.
我和妈妈的钱就是这么来的
That's how me and Mama got money.
妈妈是个很聪明的女人
Mama was a real smart lady.
记住我跟你说的话  弗里斯特
Remember what I told you, Forrest.
你和其他人没什么不同
You're no different than anybody else is.
甘氏大宅
房间出租
你听见我说的话了吗  弗里斯特
Did you hear what I said, Forrest?
你和其他人一样  没什么不同
You're the same as everybody else. You are no different.
你儿子和其他人不同  甘夫人
Your boy's different, Mrs. Gump.
他的智商只有75
Now, his IQ is 75.
我们每个人都与众不同  汉考克先生
Well, we're all different, Mr. Hancock.
她想让我接受最好的教育
She wanted me to have the finest education,
所以她带我去了绿弓县中心学校
so she took me to the Greenbow County Central School.
我见了校长
I met the principal and all.
我给你看样东西  甘夫人
I want to show you something, Mrs. Gump.
这是正常范围
Now, this is normal.
智商分数  全国平均水平
高于
正常
国家要求
低于
弗里斯特在这里
Forrest is right here.
国家要求智商至少达到80
The state requires a minimum IQ of 80
才能上公立学校  甘夫人
to attend public school, Mrs. Gump.
他得去特殊学校
He's gonna have to go to a special school.
他会没事的
Now, he'll be just fine.
"正常"到底是什么意思呢
What does "normal" mean, anyway?
他也许稍微有点迟钝
He might be a bit on the slow side,
但我儿子弗里斯特
but my boy Forrest
要得到和其他人一样的机会
is gonna get the same opportunities as everyone else.
他才不要去什么特殊学校
He's not going to some special school
学习如何更换轮胎
to learn how to re-tread tires.
只有区区5分的差距而已
We're talking about five little points here.
一定有解决办法的
There must be something can be done.
我们是先进教学体系的学校
We're a progressive school system.
我们不想看到任何人落后
We don't want to see anybody left behind.
你有丈夫吗  甘夫人
Is there a Mr. Gump, Mrs. Gump?
他在外度假
He's on vacation.
你妈妈确实很关心你的学业  孩子
Well, your mama sure does care about your schooling, son.
你的话不多  是吗
You don't say much, do you?
最后  他不得不试一试
"Finally, he had to try.
看起来简单  但是
"It looked easy, but,
天呐  发生了什么
"Oh, what happened.
-首先...  -妈  度假是什么意思
- "First, there..." - Mama, what's "vacation" mean?
-度假  -爸爸去的地方
- Vacation? - Where Daddy went.
度假就是你去一个地方
Vacation's when you go somewhere
然后再也不回来
and you don't ever come back.
总之  我想你可以说  我和妈妈只能靠自己
Anyway, I guess you could say me and Mama was on our own.
不过我们不介意  我们的房子总是住满了人
But we didn't mind. Our house was never empty.
总是有人来来去去
There was always folks coming and going.
吃晚饭了
Supper.
-吃晚饭了  各位  -天呐
- It's supper, everyone. - My, my.
-弗里斯特  -看起来真特别
- Forrest... - That sure looks special.
有时候住在我们家的人太多了
Sometimes we had so many people staying with us
每个房间都挤满了旅行者
that every room was filled with travelers.
就是那些  靠行李箱和帽箱
You know, folks living out of their suitcases
和样品箱生活的人
and hat cases and sample cases.
弗里斯特·甘  吃晚饭了  弗里斯特
Forrest Gump, it's suppertime! Forrest...
有一次  一个年轻人住在我们家
One time, a young man was staying with us,
他带着一个吉他箱
and he had him a guitar case.
弗里斯特  我跟你说了别打扰这个好心的年轻人
Forrest! I told you not to bother this nice young man.
没事的  夫人
Oh, no, that's all right, ma'am.
我只是给他展示一下吉他
I was just showing him a thing or two on the guitar here.
好吧  如果你们想吃晚饭的话  已经准备好了
All right, but your supper's ready if y'all want to eat.
好  听起来不错  谢谢  夫人
Yeah, that sounds good. Thank you, ma'am.
小家伙  再给我看看你刚刚那个疯狂的步伐
Say, man, show me that crazy little walk you just did there.
稍微慢一点
Slow it down some.
我喜欢那把吉他
I liked that guitar.
很好听
It sounded good.
我开始随着音乐移动
I started moving around to the music,
摆动我的臀部
swinging my hips.
有一天晚上  我和妈妈出去买东西
This one night, me and Mama was out shopping,
我们路过本森家居用品店
and we walked right by Benson's furniture and appliance store,
你猜怎么着
and guess what?
这不是给孩子看的
This is not for children's eyes.
几年后  那个英俊的年轻人
Some years later, that handsome young man
也就是被称为"猫王"的那个传奇
who they called "The King,"
他唱了太多的歌
well, he'd sung too many songs,
心脏病发作了
had himself a heart attack, or something.
当王一定很辛苦吧
Must be hard being a king.
有趣的是你记得一些事情
You know, it's funny how you remember some things,
但是有些事情却记不起来
but some things you can't.
你要全力以赴  弗里斯特
You do your very best now, Forrest.
我会的  妈妈
I sure will, Mama.
我清楚地记得开学第一天乘校车的情景
I remember the bus ride on the first day of school very well.
你到底要不要上车
Are you coming along?
妈妈说不要搭陌生人的车
Mama said not to be taking rides from strangers.
这是去学校的校车
This is the bus to school.
我叫弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
I'm Forrest. Forrest Gump.
我叫多洛希·哈里斯
I'm Dorothy Harris.
现在我们不是陌生人了
Well, now we ain't strangers anymore.
这个座位有人了
This seat's taken.
有人了
It's taken!
你不能坐在这里
You can't sit here.
小孩子的记忆很有趣
You know, it's funny what a young man recollects,
因为我不记得我是怎么出生的
'cause I don't remember being born.
我不记得我在第一个圣诞节收到了什么礼物
I don't recall what I got for my first Christmas,
我也不记得我第一次去野餐是什么时候
and I don't know when I went on my first outdoor picnic.
但是我清楚地记得第一次听到
But I do remember the first time I heard
那个世界上最甜美的声音
the sweetest voice in the wide world.
如果你愿意  可以坐在这里
You can sit here if you want.
我一生中从未见过如此美丽的存在
I had never seen anything so beautiful in my life.
她就像一个天使
She was like an angel.
你到底坐不坐
Well, are you gonna sit down, or aren't you?
你的腿怎么了
What's wrong with your legs?
没什么  谢谢关心  我的腿好得很
Nothing at all, thank you. My legs are just fine and dandy.
在校车上  我坐在她身旁
I just sat next to her on that bus
和她一路聊到学校
and had a conversation all the way to school.
我的脊背像问号一样弯曲
...my back's crooked like a question mark.
这些支架会让我...
These are going to make me...
除了我妈
And next to Mama,
从来没有人和我说过话或者问我问题
no one ever talked to me or asked me questions.
你是不是傻
Are you stupid or something?
妈妈说  "只有做傻事的才是傻子"
Mama says, "Stupid is as stupid does."
-我叫珍妮  -我叫弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
- I'm Jenny. - I'm Forrest. Forrest Gump.
从那天起  我们总是在一起
From that day on, we was always together.
珍妮和我形影不离
Jenny and me was like peas and carrots.
她教我怎么爬树
She taught me how to climb.
加油  弗里斯特  你能行的
Come on, Forrest, you can do it.
我教她怎么悬挂摇晃
I showed her how to dangle.
一直乖巧的小猴子和...
"A good little monkey and..."
她帮助我识字
She helped me learn how to read,
我教她怎么倒挂金钩
and I showed her how to swing.
有时候我们只是坐在外面  等着看星星
Sometimes we'd just sit out and wait for the stars.
妈妈会担心我的
Mama's gonna worry about me.
留下再多待一会儿吧
Just stay a little longer.
不知为什么  珍妮从来不想回家
For some reason, Jenny didn't never want to go home.
好的  珍妮  我留下陪你
Okay, Jenny, I'll stay.
她是我最特别的朋友
She was my most special friend.
我唯一的朋友
My only friend.
妈妈总是跟我说  奇迹每天都会发生
Now, my mama always told me that miracles happen every day.
有些人不这么认为  但是确实如此
Some people don't think so, but they do.
嘿  笨蛋
Hey, dummy!
你是弱智  还是傻子
Are you retarded, or just plain stupid?
"看啊  我是弗里斯特·瘸子"
"Look, I'm Forrest Gimp."
弗里斯特  快跑
Just run away, Forrest.
弗里斯特  快跑  快点
Run, Forrest! Run away! Hurry!
-骑车追  -快点  我们去抓他
- Get the bikes! - Hurry up! Let's get him!
-快点  -小心  笨蛋  我们来了
- Come on! - Look out, dummy, here we come!
我们会抓到你的
We're gonna get you!
弗里斯特  快跑  弗里斯特  快跑
Run, Forrest, run! Run, Forrest!
你给我回来
Come back here, you!
弗里斯特  快跑
Run, Forrest!
快跑
Run!
就算我告诉你  你也不会相信
Now, you wouldn't believe it if I told you,
但是我可以跑得像风一样快
but I can run like the wind blows.
从那天起  如果我要去什么地方
From that day on, if I was going somewhere,
我就跑着去
I was running!
他要跑了  拦住他
He's getting away! Stop him!
那孩子真是个跑得快的傻子
That boy sure is a running fool.
还记得我跟你说过
Now, remember how I told you that
珍妮似乎从来不想回家吗
Jenny never seemed to want to go home?
她住的房子有阿拉巴马州那么古老
Well, she lived in a house that was as old as Alabama.
她妈妈在她五岁时上了天堂
Her mama had gone up to heaven when she was five,
她爸爸算是个农夫
and her daddy was some kind of a farmer.
珍妮
Jenny?
他是个很有爱心的人
He was a very loving man.
他总是在亲吻抚摸珍妮和她的姐妹们
He was always kissing and touching her and her sisters.
然后有一次  珍妮没有坐校车去上学
And then this one time, Jenny wasn't on the bus to go to school.
珍妮  你今天怎么没去上学
Jenny, why didn't you come to school today?
我爸正在午睡
Daddy's taking a nap.
-珍妮  -快跑
- Jenny! - Come on!
珍妮  你要跑到哪里去
Jenny, where'd you run to?
你给我回来  死丫头
You'd better get back here, girl!
你跑到哪儿去了
Where you at?
珍妮  珍妮  你在哪儿
Jenny! Jenny! Where you at?
珍妮
Jenny!
和我一起祈祷  弗里斯特  和我一起祈祷
Pray with me, Forrest. Pray with me.
珍妮
Jenny!
亲爱的上帝  把我变成一只鸟
Dear God, make me a bird
这样我就能逃离这里  远走高飞
so I can fly far, far, far away from here.
亲爱的上帝  把我变成一只鸟
Dear God, make me a bird
这样我就能逃离这里  远走高飞
so I can fly far, far, far away from here.
妈妈总说上帝是神秘的
Mama always said that God is mysterious.
珍妮
Jenny!
那天祂没有把珍妮变成一只鸟
He didn't turn Jenny into a bird that day.
你最好给我赶快回来
You'd better get back here!
但是
Instead,
祂叫来了警察
he had the police say
说珍妮再也不用住在那个房子里了
Jenny didn't have to stay in that house no more.
她搬去和她外婆住了  就住在克里克莫尔大道
She went to live with her grandma just over on Creekmore Avenue,
我很开心  因为这样她就离我家很近了
which made me happy, 'cause she was so close.
珍妮有时晚上会偷偷溜到我家来玩
Some nights, Jenny would sneak out and come on over to my house,
只是因为她说自己害怕
just 'cause she said she was scared.
我不知道她害怕什么
Scared of what, I don't know,
但我觉得是害怕她外婆的狗
but I think it was her grandma's dog.
那是只恶犬
He was a mean dog.
不管怎样  我和珍妮直到高中
Anyway, Jenny and me was best friends
都是最好的朋友
all the way up through high school.
-嘿  蠢蛋  -住手
- Hey, stupid! - Quit it!
快跑  弗里斯特  快跑
Run, Forrest, run!
没听到我说的话吗  蠢蛋
Did you hear me, stupid?
-快跑  弗里斯特  -快点上车
- Run, Forrest! - Come on, get in the truck!
上车  快追
Get in the truck! Let's move it!
快点  他要逃了  开车
Come on, he's getting away! Move it!
快跑  弗里斯特  快跑
Run, Forrest! Run!
-你最好一直跑下去  蠢蛋  -快跑  蠢蛋
- You better be running, stupid! - Come on, dummy!
-加把劲  蠢蛋  -你最好跑快点
- Haul ass, dummy! - Yeah, you better get running!
长腿大野兔
Jack rabbit!
冲冲冲
Go! Go! Go!
快跑  弗里斯特
Run, Forrest!
我以前都是跑到哪里是哪里
Now, it used to be, I ran to get where I was going,
我从没想过自己竟然会跑出名堂
I never thought it would take me anywhere.
那他妈是谁
Who in the hell is that?
他叫弗里斯特·甘  教练
That there is Forrest Gump, Coach.
就是本地的一个白痴
Just a local idiot.
你敢信吗  我也能去上大学了
And can you believe it? I got to go to college, too.
加油
弗里斯特  弗里斯特  快跑
Forrest! Forrest! Run!
-好的  -快跑
- Okay! - Run!
快跑  你这混小子  快跑
Run, you stupid son of a bitch! Run!
加油
阿拉巴马
你这混小子  快跑  冲啊  快跑
You son of a bitch! Run! Go! Run!
不  转弯  冲啊
No! Turn! Go!
加油  阿拉巴马
他一定是这世上最蠢的白痴
He must be the stupidest son of a bitch alive,
但他是真的快
but he sure is fast!
后来  或许只有我这么觉得
Now, maybe it's just me,
但大学时光真的很迷茫
but college was very confusing times.
今天联邦政府派遣军队强制执行法院命令
Federal troops enforcing a court order
在阿拉巴马大学取缔种族隔离
integrated the University of Alabama today.
两名黑人学生获准入学
Two negroes were admitted,
但乔治·华莱士州长随后
but only after Governor George Wallace
做出象征性威胁
had carried out his symbolic threat
挡在了学校大楼门口
to stand in the school house door.
华莱士州长  那个声明上说...
Governor Wallace, I take it from that statement, that...
厄尔
Earl,
发生什么事了
what's going on?
-"浣熊"想要进学校  -浣熊
- Coons are trying to get into school. - Coons?
如果浣熊想进我家后院
When raccoons try to get on our back porch,
我妈就会用扫帚赶走它们
Mama just chase them off with a broom.
不是真的浣熊  你个白痴  是黑人
Not raccoons, you idiot, niggers,
他们想和我们一起上学
and they want to go to school with us.
和我们同校  当真吗
With us? They do?
华莱士州长履行承诺
Shortly after Governor Wallace had carried out his promise
封锁大门后不久
to block the doorway,
肯尼迪总统就命令国防部长
President Kennedy ordered the Secretary of Defense
使用武力干预
then to use military force.
本台播放的录像记录了当时国民警卫队指挥官
Here, by videotape, is the encounter by General Graham,
格兰姆将军与华莱士州长的冲突
commander of the National Guard, and Governor Wallace.
因为今日在此的国民警卫队
...because these National Guardsmen are here today
身份是阿拉巴马州的联邦士兵
as federal soldiers for Alabamans.
他们住在本州境内  他们都是我们的兄弟
They live within our borders, they are all our brothers.
我们取得了这场战争的胜利
We are winning in this fight,
因为我们正在唤醒美国人民
because we are awakening the American people
看清我们此前多次强调的危机
to the dangers that we have spoken about so many times,
今日之事再次证明
just so evident today,
本国正在走向军事独裁
the trend towards military dictatorship in this country.
因此  当晚  位于塔斯卡卢萨的阿拉巴马大学
And so, at day's end, the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa
废除了种族隔离
had been desegregated
吉米·胡德和薇薇安·马隆两位学生
and students Jimmy Hood and Vivian Malone
已经报名参加了暑期班
had been signed up for summer classes.
女士  你的书掉了  女士
Ma'am, you dropped your book. Ma'am...
华莱士州长履行了承诺
Governor Wallace did what he promised to do.
在塔斯卡卢萨的校园内
By being on the Tuscaloosa campus,
成功阻止了暴徒集聚
he kept the mob from gathering...
那不是阿甘吗
Say, wasn't that Gump?
不  不可能
Nah, that couldn't be.
肯定是他
It sure as hell was.
几年后
A few years later,
那个生气地挡在学校大楼门口的小男人
that angry little man at the school house door
觉得竞选总统会是个好主意
thought it would be a good idea and ran for president.
但有人觉得这不是个好主意
But somebody thought that it wasn't.
不过他没死
But he didn't die.
我等的公交车到了
My bus is here.
-是9路车吗  -不  是4路车
- Is it the number nine? - No, it's the number four.
很高兴和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
我记得当时华莱士遇刺的时候
I remember when that happened, when Wallace got shot.
我还在上大学
I was in college.
你上的是女校
Did you go to a girls' college,
还是男女混校
or to a girls-and-boys-together college?
男女混校
It was co-ed.
珍妮上的大学我就不能去上
'Cause Jenny went to a college I couldn't go to.
那个大学只收女生
It was a college just for girls.
但我一有机会就会去看她
But I'd go and visit her every chance I got.
好疼
That hurts.
弗里斯特  弗里斯特
Forrest! Forrest!
弗里斯特  住手  住手
Forrest, stop it! Stop it!
你在干什么
What are you doing?
-他在伤害你  -这他妈是什么情况
- He was hurting you. - What the hell is going on here?
-不  他没有  去那边  -他是谁  他是谁
- No, he's not! Get over there! - Who is that? Who is that?
-比利  对不起  -什么情况
- Billy, I'm sorry. - What the hell?
-离我远点  -不要
- Just get away from me! - Don't...
-不要走  比利  等等  -离我远点
- Don't go! Billy, wait a second! - Get away from me.
他完全不懂事的
He doesn't know any better!
弗里斯特  你为什么要那样做
Forrest, why did you do that?
我给你带了点巧克力来
I brought you some chocolate.
对不起
I'm sorry.
-我现在就回学校了  -弗里斯特
- I'll go back to my college now. - Forrest...
看看你这样子
Look at you.
来吧  来吧
Come on. Come on.
这是你的寝室吗
Is this your room?
弗里斯特  你是否会梦想着
Do you ever dream, Forrest,
自己想成为什么样的人
about who you're gonna be?
-我要成为什么样的人  -是啊
- Who I'm gonna be? - Yeah.
难道我不再是我自己了吗
Aren't I going to be me?
你永远都会是你  只是你还有其他可能
Well, you'll always be you, just another kind of you.
明白吗
You know?
我想出名
I want to be famous.
我想成为像琼·贝兹一样的歌手
I want to be a singer like Joan Baez.
我只想站在空旷的舞台上
I just want to be on an empty stage
那里只有我的吉他和歌声
with my guitar, my voice.
只有我自己
Just me.
我想触动人们的内心
And I want to reach people on the personal level.
我想拥有与人一对一交心的能力
I want to be able to say things, just one-to-one.
你和女孩在一起过吗  弗里斯特
Have you ever been with a girl, Forrest?
我上家政课的时候一直和她们坐在一起
I sit next to them in my Home Economics class all the time.
-对不起  -没事的
- I'm... Sorry. - It's okay.
没事的
It's all right.
-没事的  -我头晕了
- It's okay. - Oh, I'm dizzy.
我想你在家政课上没做过这个吧
I bet that never happened in Home Ec.
没有
No.
我想我弄脏了你舍友的浴袍
I think I ruined your roommate's bathrobe.
没关系  反正我也不喜欢她
I don't care. I don't like her, anyway.
加油
跑  跑  跑
Run! Run! Run!
-跑  跑  跑  -跑  跑  跑
- Run! Run! Run! - Run! Run! Run!
弗里斯特
加油  阿拉巴马
停
弗里斯特
大学生活过得飞快
College ran by real fast,
因为我参加太多橄榄球比赛了
'cause I played so much football.
他们还把我弄进了全美明星队
They even put me on a thing called the All-America Team,
派拉蒙新闻报道
进去后可以见到美国总统
where you get to meet the President of the United States.
肯尼迪总统今天
President Kennedy met with
在白宫办公室接见了全美大学生橄榄球队
the Collegiate All-American Football Team at the Oval Office today.
会见美国总统
Now, the really good thing about meeting
最大的好处就是有好吃的
the President of the United States is the food.
他们会安排你坐在一个小厅里
They put you in this little room
里面吃的喝的都应有尽有
with just about anything you'd want to eat or drink.
但是  第一  我不饿  但是渴
And since, number one, I wasn't hungry, but thirsty,
第二  饮料是免费的
and number two, they was free,
我大概喝了15瓶汽水
I must have drank me about 15 Dr. Peppers.
恭喜  入选全美明星队感觉如何
Congratulations. How does it feel to be an All-American?
很荣幸  长官
It's an honor, sir.
恭喜  入选全美明星队感觉如何
Congratulations. How does it feel to be an All-American?
很好  长官
Very good, sir.
恭喜  入选全美明星队感觉如何
Congratulations. How does it feel to be an All-American?
很好  长官
Very good, sir.
-恭喜  你感觉如何  -我想尿尿
- Congratulations. How do you feel? - I gotta pee.
我好像听到他说他要尿尿
I believe he said he had to "Go pee."
不久后  莫名其妙地
Sometime later, for no particular reason,
有人枪杀了这位年轻的好总统
somebody shot that nice young President,
当时他正坐在车里
when he was riding in his car.
过了几年
And a few years after that,
又有人枪杀了他的弟弟
somebody shot his little brother, too,
只不过他当时是在酒店厨房里
only he was in a hotel kitchen.
做兄弟也太难了
It must be hard being brothers.
我反正没机会体会这点
I wouldn't know.
弗里斯特·甘
Forrest Gump.
你敢相信吗
Now can you believe it?
我只不过玩了五年橄榄球
After only five years of playing football,
竟然拿到了大学学位
I got a college degree.
祝贺你  孩子
Congratulations, son.
我妈骄傲极了
Mama was so proud.
弗里斯特  我太为你骄傲了  我帮你拿这个
Forrest, I'm so proud of you. Here, I'll hold this for you.
祝贺你  孩子
Congratulations, son.
你对自己的未来有没有什么想法
Have you given any thought to your future?
想法
Thought?
青年才俊
踊跃参军
你好  我是弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
Hello, I'm Forrest. Forrest Gump.
没人在乎你他妈是什么狗东西  混球
Nobody gives a hunk of shit who you are, fuzzball!
你连低等生物都不如  吃屎的蛆
You're not even a low-life, scum-sucking maggot!
滚去你的座位上  你现在是在军队
Get your faggotty ass on the bus. You're in the Army now!
这个座位有人了
This seat's taken.
有人了
Taken.
一开始  我觉得自己做了个错误的决定
At first, it seemed like I made a mistake,
因为入伍的第一天
seeing how it was only my induction day
我就被人无情地怒吼了
and I was already getting yelled at.
如果你愿意  可以坐在这里
You can sit down if you want to.
我不知道自己会遇到什么人  或者被问什么问题
I didn't know who I might meet, or what they might ask.
你有没有乘过真正的捕虾船
You ever been on a real shrimp boat?
没有  但我乘过很大的船
No, but I been on a real big boat.
我说的是一种专门捕虾的船
I'm talking about a shrimp-catching boat.
我一辈子都在捕虾船上干活
I've been working on shrimp boats all my life.
我一开始是在我舅舅的船上  就是我妈妈的弟弟
I started out on my uncle's boat, that's my mama's brother,
当时我可能大概9岁吧
when I was about maybe nine.
我本想买一艘自己的船  然后却被强制入伍了
I was just looking into buying a boat of my own and got drafted.
我的名字是本杰明·巴福德·布鲁
My given name is Benjamin Buford Blue.
大家都叫我巴巴
People call me Bubba.
就像以前南方佬常用的名字
Just like one of them old redneck boys.
你敢信吗
Can you believe that?
我的名字是弗里斯特·甘
My name's Forrest Gump.
大家都叫我弗里斯特·甘
People call me Forrest Gump.
巴巴来自阿拉巴马州的拜尤拉巴特里
So, Bubba was from Bayou La Batre, Alabama,
他妈妈是煮虾的
and his mama cooked shrimp,
他的外婆也是煮虾的
and her mama before her cooked shrimp,
他的外曾祖母也是煮虾的
and her mama before her mama cooked shrimp, too.
巴巴的家族
Bubba's family
对整个虾行业都知道得一清二楚
knew everything there was to know about the shrimping business.
我对整个虾行业都知道得一清二楚
I know everything there is to know about the shrimping business.
实际上  我打算
Matter of fact, I'm going into
等退伍之后  也投身虾行业
the shrimping business for myself after I get out the Army.
好吧
Okay.
阿甘  你是为了什么来参军的
Gump! What's your sole purpose in this Army?
为了完成你下达的任何指令  德尔中士
To do whatever you tell me, Drill Sergeant!
该死的  阿甘  你真他妈是个天才
God damn it, Gump! You're a goddamn genius!
这是我听过的最优秀的答案
That's the most outstanding answer I've ever heard.
你的智商一定有他们的160分
You must have a goddamn IQ of 160!
你真他妈有天赋  二等兵甘
You are goddamn gifted, Private Gump!
全体都听好了
Listen up, people!
不知为何
Now, for some reason,
我在军队里混得如鱼得水
I fit in the Army like one of them round pegs.
这真的并不难
It's not really hard.
你只需把床铺得很整齐
You just make your bed real neat
记得站直
and remember to stand up straight,
并且总是用"是  德尔中士"来回答所有问题
and always answer every question with, "Yes, Drill Sergeant!"
听明白了吗
Is that clear?
是  德尔中士
Yes, Drill Sergeant!
你只需要贴着海底拖渔网
What you do is, you just drag your nets along the bottom.
运气好的话  你一次就能捕到100多磅的虾
On a good day, you can catch over 100 pounds of shrimp.
如果一切顺利的话  两个人捕虾十个小时
If everything goes all right, two men shrimping 10 hours,
再减去油费  就能...
less what you spend on gas, you can...
装完了  德尔中士
Done, Drill Sergeant!
阿甘
Gump!
你为什么组装枪这么快  阿甘
Why did you put that weapon together so quickly, Gump?
你让我这么做的  德尔中士
You told me to, Drill Sergeant.
我的上帝  你创了本连的新纪录
Jesus H. Christ, this is a new company record.
要不是担心浪费了这么好的一个兵
If it wouldn't be a waste of such a damn fine enlisted man,
我真想推荐你去候补军官学校  二等兵甘
I'd recommend you for OCS, Private Gump.
你将来一定能成为一名将军  阿甘
You are gonna be a general some day, Gump.
现在拆开你的枪  重新组装
Now, disassemble your weapon and continue!
就像我刚刚说过的  虾就是大海结出的果实
Anyway, like I was saying, shrimp is the fruit of the sea.
你可以做烤虾  水煮虾  炒虾
You can barbecue it, boil it, broil it, bake it, sauté it.
可以做烤虾串  克里奥尔烩虾...
There's shrimp kebabs, shrimp Creole...
虾浓汤  平锅煎虾  油炸虾  清炒虾
...shrimp gumbo, pan fried, deep fried, stir fried.
还有菠萝虾  柠檬虾
There's pineapple shrimp, lemon shrimp,
椰子虾  胡椒虾...
coconut shrimp, pepper shrimp...
鲜虾汤  烩虾  鲜虾沙拉  虾肉炖土豆
...shrimp soup, shrimp stew, shrimp salad, shrimp and potatoes,
虾肉汉堡  鲜虾三明治...
shrimp burger, shrimp sandwich...
差...差不多就这些了
That's... That's about it.
军队里的夜晚格外孤独
Night time in the Army is a lonely time.
我们会躺在床铺上
We'd lay there in our bunks
我会想念我妈妈
and I'd miss my mama.
我还会想念珍妮
And I'd miss Jenny.
阿甘
Gump,
好好看看她的胸吧
get a load of the tits on her!
结果发现  珍妮惹上了一些麻烦
Turns out, Jenny had gotten into some trouble
因为她穿着校服拍了几张照片
over some photos of her in her college sweater,
所以她被学校开除了
and she was thrown out of school.
不过这也并非一件坏事
But that wasn't a bad thing,
因为一个在田纳西州孟菲斯有剧场的人
because a man who owns a theater in Memphis, Tennessee,
看到了那些照片
saw those photos
然后给珍妮提供了一份登台唱歌的工作
and offered Jenny a job singing in a show.
我一有机会休假
The first chance I got,
就马上乘大巴去孟菲斯  去看她的表演
I took the bus up to Memphis to see her perform in that show.
刚刚表演的是安波  安波·弗莱姆
That was Amber, Amber Flame.
请大家为她热烈鼓掌  好样的  安波
Give her a big hand, guys. Good job, Amber.
接下来  为您带来视听双重享受的是
And now, for your listening and viewing pleasure,
来自加州好莱坞的  我们跨掉一代的美人
direct from Hollywood, California, our very own beatnik beauty,
让我们热烈欢迎性感的芭比·迪伦
let's give a big round of applause to the luscious Bobbi Dylan.
-好极了  -芭比
- All right! - Bobbi!
♪一个男人要走过多少路♪
♪How many roads must a man walk down♪
♪才能称为真正的男人♪
♪Before you can call him a man♪
♪一只白鸽要飞越过多少片大海♪
♪How many seas must a white dove sail♪
♪才能在沙滩上安睡♪
♪Before she sleeps in the sand♪
她的梦想已经成真了
Her dream had come true.
她成了民谣歌手了
She was a folk singer.
♪炮弹要多少次掠过天空♪
♪How many times must the cannon balls fly♪
♪才能永远被废止♪
♪Before they're forever banned♪
来呀  宝贝  扭起来  抖起来嘛
Come on, baby. Shake it up. Shake it up, now.
嘿  伙计  给她换个口琴
Hey, buddy, get her a harmonica.
♪我的朋友啊  这些问题的答案在风中飘扬♪
♪The answer, my friend, is blowin' in the wind♪
嘿  甜心  这可不是《袋鼠船长》[儿童节目]
Hey, honey, this ain't Captain Kangaroo.
嘿  甜心  我有东西要送给你哦
Hey, honey, I got something here for you.
该死的
God damn it!
你个蠢货混蛋
Stupid jerk!
我在这唱着歌呢
I'm singing a song here.
波利  滚出去
Polly, get out here!
-闭嘴  滚  -别害羞嘛  甜心
- Shut up, there! - Don't be so shy, honey.
闭嘴
Oh, shut up!
弗里斯特  你在这干什么
Forrest, what are you doing here?
你要干什么
What are you doing?
-拜托  -你要干什么
- Come on. - What are you doing?
弗里斯特  放下我
Forrest, let me down!
你不能一直这样做  弗里斯特
You can't keep doing this, Forrest.
你不能一直试图来拯救我
You can't keep trying to rescue me all the time.
-他们刚刚想摸你  -很多人都想摸我
- They was trying to grab you. - A lot of people try to grab me.
但...你不能一直这样做
Just... You can't keep doing this all the time.
我控制不了
I can't help it.
我爱你
I love you.
弗里斯特  你根本不知道什么是爱
Forrest, you don't know what love is.
你还记得那次我们祷告吗  弗里斯特
You remember that time we prayed, Forrest?
我们向上帝祷告  希望祂能把我变成一只鸟
We prayed for God to turn me into a bird
这样我就可以飞走了  飞得远远的
so I could fly far, far away?
是的  我记得
Yes, I do.
你觉得我能飞下这座大桥吗
You think I could fly off this bridge?
你什么意思  珍妮
What do you mean, Jenny?
没什么
Nothing.
我必须离开这里
I gotta get out of here.
等等  珍妮
Wait, Jenny...
弗里斯特  你离我远点  好吗
Forrest, you stay away from me, okay?
求你离我远点
You just stay away from me, please.
能搭个顺风车吗
Can I have a ride?
-你要去哪儿  -随便
- Where you going? - I don't care.
上车吧
Get in the truck.
再见  珍妮
So, bye-bye, Jenny.
他们要派我去越南
They sending me to Vietnam.
那是另外一个国家
It's this whole other country.
稍等一下
Just hang on a minute.
听着  你要向我保证一件事  好吗
Listen, you promise me something, okay?
万一你碰到危险  不要逞强
Just, if you're ever in trouble, don't try to be brave.
你只管跑  好吗
You just run, okay?
跑得远远的
Just run away.
好的
Okay.
珍妮
Jenny.
我会一直给你写信的
I'll write you all the time.
就那样  她上车走了
And just like that, she was gone.
你一定要平安回来  听见了吗
You come back safe to me, do you hear?
他们告诉我们在越南和在美国服役相比
Now, they told us that Vietnam was gonna be very different
将会完全不一样
from the United States of America.
但除了成箱的啤酒和野外烧烤外  的确如此
And except for all the beer cans and the barbecue, it was.
我猜这片水域里一定有虾
I bet there's shrimp all in these waters.
他们跟我说这些越南人都很会捕虾
They tell me these Vietnams is good shrimpers.
等我们打赢了仗  我们就能接管一切
You know, after we win this war, and we take over everything,
我们就能让美国的捕虾者
we can get American shrimpers
来到这里  在这片水域里捕虾
to come out here and shrimp these waters.
我们只要一直捕虾就好了
We'll just shrimp all the time, man.
很多很多的虾
So much shrimp.
你们一定是我的新兵吧
You must be my FNGs.
-早安  长官  -早安  长官
- Morning, sir! - Morning, sir!
把手放下  别向我行礼
Get your hands down! Do not salute me.
这附近有很多该死的狙击手
There's goddamn snipers all around this area
最喜欢射杀军官
who would love to grease an officer.
我是丹·泰勒中尉  欢迎来到四排
I'm Lieutenant Dan Taylor. Welcome to Fourth Platoon.
你的嘴唇怎么了
What's wrong with your lip?
我天生嘴唇厚  长官
I was born with big gums, sir.
好吧  那你最好把嘴唇吸回去
Yeah, well, you better tuck that in.
不然容易碰到地雷线
Gonna get that caught on a trip wire.
你们两个老家都是哪里的
Where you boys from in the world?
-阿拉巴马州  长官  -阿拉巴马州  长官
- Alabama, sir! - Alabama, sir!
你们是双胞胎吗
You twins?
不是  我们没有血缘关系  长官
No, we are not relations, sir.
听着  这边规矩很简单
Look, it's pretty basic here.
只要你们跟着我
If you stick with me
向在这里待了一段时间的老兵好好学习
and learn from the guys who've been in country a while,
你们会没事的
you'll be all right.
只有一样必备的军需品
There is one item of GI gear
它将关系到你们的生死存亡
that can be the difference between a live grunt and a dead grunt.
就是袜子  底部有衬垫  绿色的袜子
Socks. Cushion sole, OD green.
尽量保持双脚干燥
Try and keep your feet dry.
我们负重出行的时候  你们一定要记住
When we're out humping, I want you boys to remember
只要停下休整  就要换干爽的袜子
to change your socks whenever we stop.
不然湄公河会泡烂你的脚
The Mekong will eat a grunt's feet right off his legs.
希姆斯中士  该死的
Sergeant Sims, God damn it,
我让你申报的吊索在哪呢
where is that sling rope I told you to order?
我已经写在军队的申请单上了
I put in the requisitions at Battalion.
好吧  好吧  那你再给那群混蛋打电话...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, well, you call those sons of bitches again...
丹中尉对军队的事务十分熟悉
Lieutenant Dan sure knew his stuff.
他能做我的中尉  我真是太幸运了
I felt real lucky he was my lieutenant.
他出身于战功显赫的军人世家
He was from a long, great military tradition.
美国历史上的每一场战争
Somebody in his family had fought and died
他的家人都曾参与并战死其中
in every single American war.
-该死的  使劲催  -马上去办  中尉
- God damn it, kick some ass! - I'm on it, Lieutenant.
赶快去办
Get on it!
或许可以说  他要达到祖辈的丰功伟绩需要艰苦奋斗
I guess you could say he had a lot to live up to.
所以你们都是来自阿肯色州的  对吧
So, you boys are from Arkansas, huh?
我去过那里
I've been through there.
小石城是个好地方
Little Rock's a fine town.
现在放下你们的装备  去找排长
Now, go shake down your gear, see the platoon sergeant,
领你们上阵需要的东西
draw what you need for the field.
如果你们饿了  那边正烤着牛排呢
If you boys are hungry, we got steaks burning right over here.
本排有两条守则
Two standing orders in this platoon:
一  照顾好你的脚
one, take good care of your feet,
二  不要干蠢事  比如害死自己之类的
two, try not to do anything stupid, like getting yourself killed.
我真希望我不会让他失望
I sure hope I don't let him down.
我可以经常看到乡下的风光
I got to see a lot of the countryside.
我们经常会走很长的路
We would take these real long walks.
我们一直在找一个叫查理[越共]的家伙
And we were always looking for this guy named Charlie.
-停下  -停下  各位
- Hold it up! - Hold up, boys!
但并非一直是快乐有趣的
It wasn't always fun.
丹中尉总是
Lieutenant Dan was always
会对路上的风吹草动有着古怪的直觉
getting these funny feelings about a rock, or a trail, or the road,
然后他会叫我们趴下  闭嘴...
so he'd tell us to get down, shut up...
趴下  闭嘴
Get down! Shut up!
于是我们照做
...so we did.
虽然我对所有事情都不太懂
Now, I don't know much about anything,
但我觉得美国一批最出色的年轻人
but I think some of America's best young men
都投入到了这场战争中
served in this war.
比如  来自凤凰城的达拉斯
There was Dallas, from Phoenix,
来自底特律的克利夫兰
Cleveland, he was from Detroit.
泰克斯  泰克斯
Tex. Hey, Tex.
前面到底怎么了
Man, what the hell's going on?
泰克斯来自...
And Tex was...
我不记得泰克斯来自哪里了
Well, I don't remember where Tex come from.
没事
Nothing.
四排  起立
Fourth Platoon, on your feet.
距离那条河还有十公里  出发
Still got 10 klicks to go to that river. Move out.
快点  出发
Come on, move out.
快跟上  快点  打起精神来
Step it up. Look alive out there.
在越南最好的一点
The good thing about Vietnam
就是总会有地方可去
is there was always some place to go.
小心手雷
Fire in the hole!
阿甘  检查一下那个洞
Gump, check out that hole.
而且也总是有事可做
And there was always something to do.
-跟上  -散开  掩护他
- Mount them up. - Spread out! Cover his back.
有一天  突然开始下雨
One day, it started raining,
整整下了四个月
and it didn't quit for four months.
我们经历了各种各样的雨
We'd been through every kind of rain there is:
小小的淅沥沥的雨
little bitty stinging rain,
大大的哗啦啦的雨
and big old fat rain,
伴着狂风的暴雨
rain that flew in sideways.
有时候  雨甚至像是从地下冒上来的
And sometimes, rain even seemed to come straight up from underneath.
糟糕  连晚上也下雨
Shoot, it even rained at night.
-嘿  弗里斯特  -你好  巴巴
- Hey, Forrest. - Hey, Bubba.
我要靠在你身上
I'm gonna lean up against you.
你也靠在我身上
You just lean right back against me.
这样的话  我们的头就不用枕在泥里了
This way, we don't have to sleep with our heads in the mud.
你知道为什么我们是一对好搭档吗  弗里斯特
You know why we a good partnership, Forrest?
因为我们会互相关照彼此
'Cause we be watching out for one another,
就像兄弟一样
like brothers and stuff.
弗里斯特  我一直在想一件事
Forrest, there's something I've been thinking about.
我有个非常重要的问题要问你
I got a very important question to ask you.
你想不想跟我一起做捕虾的行当
How would you like to go into the shrimping business with me?
好啊
Okay.
我告诉你  我也全都想清楚了
Man, I tell you what, I got it all figured out, too.
要捕多少磅虾才能付清买船的钱
So many pounds of shrimp to pay off the boat,
捕多少磅虾付油钱  我们可以直接住在船上
so many pounds for gas, we can just live right on the boat.
那样就不用交房租了
We ain't got to pay no rent.
我来当船长  我们可以合作
I'll be the captain, we can just work it together,
所有收入对半分
split everything right down the middle.
我告诉你  一人一半
Man, I'm telling you, 50-50.
弗里斯特  你想吃多少虾都有
And, hey, Forrest, all the shrimp you can eat.
那真是个好主意
That's a fine idea.
巴巴确实想出了个好主意
Bubba did have a fine idea.
我甚至写信给珍妮  把这事告诉了她
I even wrote Jenny and told her all about it.
我经常给她写信  虽不是每天都写  但也差不多了
I sent her letters, not every day, but almost.
我会告诉她我在做什么
I told her what I was doing
问她都在做什么
and asked her what she was doing,
告诉她我一直以来有多想她
and told her how I thought about her always,
以及我有多么期盼收到她的信
and how I was looking forward to getting a letter from her
前提是她有时间回信
just as soon as she had the time.
我总是让她知道我平安无事
I'd always let her know that I was okay.
然后在每封信的落款  我会写上
Then, I'd sign each letter,
"爱你的  弗里斯特·甘"
"Love, Forrest Gump."
有一天  我们走在外面  就像平常一样
This one day, we was out walking, like always,
然后  就这样
and then, just like that,
好像有人把雨关停了  太阳出来了
somebody turned off the rain and the sun come out.
有埋伏
Ambush!
找掩护
Take cover!
趴下
Get down!
拿M60机枪
Get the sixty!
快把机关枪拿过来  该死的
Get that pig up here, God damn it!
弗里斯特  你没事吧
Forrest, you okay?
铁腕  铁腕  请注意  铁腕
Strongarm! Strongarm! Be advised, Strongarm!
医务兵  这边有一个人受伤了
Medic, we got a man down!
铁腕  这里是利马腿6号小队  完毕
Strongarm, this is Leg Lima 6, over!
收到  铁腕
Roger, Strongarm,
请注意
be advised
我们在「B+2」地点的林木线附近遭遇敌袭
we have incoming from the tree line at point blue plus two.
有AK步枪和火箭弹
AKs and rockets...
枪射不出  无法射击
Misfire! Misfire!
该死的  麦克
God damn it! Mac!
把那玩意儿...  操  先进森林里去
Get that thing... Fuck it, get it in the tree line!
天呐
Jesus!
我的小队遭受重创
My unit is down hard and hurting!
6号小队撤退回蓝线  利马腿6号结束通话
Six are pulling back to Blue Line, Leg Lima 6 out.
撤退  撤退
Pull back! Pull back!
快跑  快跑  弗里斯特
Run! Run, Forrest!
-撤退  -弗里斯特  弗里斯特
- Pull back! - Forrest, Forrest!
快跑  兄弟  快跑
Run, man! Run!
撤退  快跑
Pull back! Run!
快跑  该死的  快跑
Run, God damn it, run!
医务兵  有医务兵吗
Medic! Can I get a medic?
我跑啊跑  就像珍妮叫我做的那样
I ran and ran, just like Jenny told me to.
我跑得太远太快  很快就只剩下我独自一人
I ran so far and so fast that pretty soon I was all by myself,
这可不太妙
which was a bad thing.
巴巴
Bubba!
巴巴是我最亲最好的朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
我得确保他平安无事
I had to make sure that he was okay.
还有自己人吗
Any friendlies out there?
有  我这里有三个
Yeah, I've got three over here.
你到底在哪儿
Where the hell are you?
巴巴
Bubba?
在我回去找巴巴的路上
And on my way back to find Bubba,
我发现了一个男孩躺在地上
well, there was this boy laying on the ground.
泰克斯
Tex!
好的
Okay.
我不能任由他一个人躺在那里
I couldn't just let him lay there all alone,
他惊魂未定  极度恐惧
scared the way he was,
所以我扛起他  带他跑了出去
so I grabbed him up and run him out of there.
每次我回去找巴巴时
And every time I went back looking for Bubba,
都有别人在喊  "救救我  弗里斯特  救救我"
somebody else was saying, "Help me, Forrest. Help me."
听不见  听不见
Can't hear... Can't hear...
别担心  兄弟  躺着就好
No sweat, man. Just lay back.
你会没事的  你会没事的
You'll be okay. You'll be okay.
我渐渐开始害怕我可能永远也找不到巴巴了
I started to get scared that I might never find Bubba.
完毕
Over.
收到  铁腕  我知道我的位置非常危险
Roger, Strongarm, I know my position is danger close.
我们这片区域全是越共
We got Charlie all over this area.
我需要喷气战斗机马上过来  完毕
I gotta have those fast movers in here now. Over.
6号小队  这里是铁腕  我们想...
Six, Strongarm, we want...
丹中尉  科尔曼死了
Lieutenant Dan, Coleman's dead!
我知道他死了
I know he's dead!
我的整个排都他妈被灭了
My whole goddamn platoon is wiped out!
-利马腿6号  利马腿6号  -该死的
- Leg Lima 6, Leg Lima 6. - God damn it!
-是否收到信息  完毕  -你在干什么
- Copy this transmission. Over. - What are you doing?
别管我  走开  别碰我
Just leave me here! Get away. Just leave me here!
-滚  -利马腿6号  铁腕  收到吗  完毕
- Get out! - Leg Lima 6, Strongarm. How copy this? Over.
天呐  我说了不要管我  该死的
God, I said leave me here, God damn it!
利马腿6号  利马腿6号
Leg Lima 6, Leg Lima 6,
这里是铁腕  请注意
this is Strongarm, be advised
喷射战斗机马上到达你处  完毕
your fast movers are inbound at this time, over.
然后我感觉有东西跳起来咬了我一口
Then, it felt like something just jumped up and bit me.
有东西咬了我
Something bit me!
你们这些亚洲傻逼
You chink son of a bitch!
我不能丢下我的排
I can't leave the platoon.
我让你别管我  阿甘
I told you to leave me there, Gump.
别管我了  你自己跑吧
Forget about me. Get yourself out!
你听到我说的了吗
Did you hear what I said?
该死的  把我放下来
God damn it, put me down!
你自己滚吧
Get your ass out of here!
我没让你救我离开  你他妈的
I didn't ask you to pull me out of there, God damn you!
你以为你要去哪儿
Where the hell do you think you're going?
去找巴巴
To get Bubba.
我已经呼叫进行空中打击了
I got an air strike inbound right now.
他们会用汽油弹轰炸整片区域
They're gonna nape the whole area.
阿甘  你给我待在这里  该死的  这是命令
Gump, you stay here, God damn it! That's an order!
我一定要找到巴巴
I gotta find Bubba!
弗里斯特
Forrest.
-巴巴  -我没事  弗里斯特
- Bubba. - I'm okay, Forrest.
我没事
I'm okay.
巴巴  不...
Oh, Bubba, no...
不  我会没事的
Nah, I'm gonna be all right.
来吧  来吧  来吧
Come on. Come on. Come on.
我没事  弗里斯特
I'm okay, Forrest.
我没事  兄弟  我挺好的
I'm okay, man. I'm fine.
轰炸机来了  快离开那里
Helo's inbound. Top smoke, get it out there!
如果我知道这将会是我
If I'd a known this was gonna
最后一次和巴巴说话
be the last time me and Bubba was gonna talk,
我会想到一些更好的话来说
I'd of thought of something better to say.
嘿  巴巴
Hey, Bubba.
嘿  弗里斯特
Hey, Forrest.
弗里斯特  为什么会这样
Forrest, why'd this happen?
你中枪了
You got shot.
然后巴巴说了一句话  让我终生难忘
Then Bubba said something I won't ever forget.
我想回家
I wanna go home.
巴巴是我最亲最好的朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
就连我也知道
And even I know that ain't
这样的朋友不是随随便便就能找到的
something you can find just around the corner.
巴巴本来要成为一名捕虾船的船长
Bubba was gonna be a shrimping boat captain,
但结果他死在了越南的那条河边
but instead he died right there by that river in Vietnam.
我要说的就是这些
That's all I have to say about that.
那是颗子弹  对吧
It was a bullet, wasn't it?
-子弹  -那个跳起来咬你的东西
- A bullet? - That jumped up and bit you.
是的  先生
Oh, yes, sir.
直接咬在了我的屁股上
Bit me directly in the buttocks.
他们说这是个「价值百万美元的伤」
They said it was a million-dollar wound,
实际是指所受的伤严重到
可以从前线被撤出
但又不会致命或永久致残
但那笔钱肯定被军队吞下了
but the Army must keep that money,
因为我到现在也没看到一百万美元的影子
'cause I still ain't seen a nickel of that million dollars.
屁股受伤的唯一好处
The only good thing about being wounded in the buttocks
就是有冰淇淋吃
is the ice cream.
他们给了我吃不完的冰淇淋
They gave me all the ice cream I could eat.
猜猜怎么着
And guess what?
我的一个好朋友就在我旁边那张床
A good friend of mine was in the bed right next door.
丹中尉  我给你拿了冰淇淋
Lieutenant Dan, I got you some ice cream.
丹中尉  冰淇淋
Lieutenant Dan, ice cream.
到洗澡时间了  中尉
It's time for your bath, Lieutenant.
哈珀
Harper!
库珀  拉森
Cooper, Larson,
韦伯斯特
Webster.
-阿甘  阿甘  -我是弗里斯特·甘
- Gump. Gump. - I'm Forrest Gump.
凯尔
Kyle,
尼科尔斯
Nichols,
退还寄信人
一等兵
弗里斯特·甘
珍妮·库伦  收
麦克米尔
McMill,
退还寄信人
一等兵
弗里斯特·甘
珍妮·库伦  收
约翰逊
Johnson,
泰勒
Tyler,
霍利迪
Holiday...
惊喜  惊喜  惊喜
Surprise, surprise, surprise!
阿甘  你怎么能看这么蠢的玩意儿
Gump, how can you watch that stupid shit?
关掉
Turn it off!
您现在收看的是美军越南电视网
you are tuned to the American Forces Vietnam Network.
这里是在西贡的6频道
This is Channel 6, Saigon.
接得好  阿甘
Good catch, Gump.
你知道这个怎么打吗
You know how to play this?
来吧  我给你演示下  过来
Come on, let me show you. Here.
这个运动的秘诀就是
Now, the secret to this game is,
无论发生什么
no matter what happens,
绝对不要让你的视线离开球
never ever take your eye off the ball.
好的
All right.
不知为何  我似乎天生就会打乒乓球
For some reason, Ping-Pong came very natural to me.
看到了吧  傻子都能打
See? Any idiot can play.
于是我开始整天打乒乓球
So, I started playing it all the time.
我可以在没人陪我打时  一个人打得很起劲
I played Ping-Pong even when I didn't have anyone to play Ping-Pong with.
医院里的人说我看起来像水里的鸭子[如鱼得水]
The hospital's people said it made me look like a duck in water,
管它什么意思呢
whatever that means.
连丹中尉都会来看我打球
Even Lieutenant Dan would come and watch me play.
我乒乓打得太多  甚至连睡梦中也在打
I played Ping-Pong so much, I even played it in my sleep.
你听我说  我们都有自己的宿命
Now, you listen to me. We all have a destiny.
没有什么是随便发生的  一切都是命中注定
Nothing just happens, it's all part of a plan.
我本来应该在那里和我的兵一起死掉
I should have died out there with my men,
但我现在只不过是一个该死的残废
but now I'm nothing but a goddamn cripple,
一个没有腿的怪物  看  你看看我
a legless freak! Look! Look! Look at me!
你看见了吗
Do you see that?
你知道没办法使用自己的腿是什么感受吗
Do you know what it's like not to be able to use your legs?
是的  长官  我知道
Yes, sir, I do.
你听见我说的了吗
Did you hear what I said?
你篡改了我的命运
You cheated me.
我本来有自己的宿命
I had a destiny.
我本应该光荣地死在战场上
I was supposed to die in the field, with honor!
这才是我的宿命  你篡改了我的命运
That was my destiny, and you cheated me out of it!
你明白我在说什么吗  阿甘
Do you understand what I'm saying, Gump?
这种事不应该发生在我身上
This wasn't supposed to happen, not to me.
我本来有自己的宿命
I had a destiny.
我曾是丹·泰勒中尉
I was Lieutenant Dan Taylor.
你现在还是丹中尉
You're still Lieutenant Dan.
看看我的样子
Look at me.
我现在要怎么办
What am I gonna do now?
陆军一等兵阿甘
PFC Gump?
是  长官
Yes, sir!
继续做你的事
As you were.
孩子  你获得荣誉勋章了
Son, you've been awarded the Medal of Honor.
你猜怎么着  丹中尉  他们想给我一个...
Guess what, Lieutenant Dan, they want to give me a...
女士
Ma'am,
他们把丹中尉怎么了
what'd they do with Lieutenant Dan?
他们送他回家了
They sent him home.
两周后  我离开了越南
Two weeks later, I left Vietnam.
在仪式开始时  总统发表了关于
The ceremony was kicked off with a candid speech by the President
扩大越南战争必要性的坦率讲话
regarding the need for further escalation of the war in Vietnam.
约翰逊总统向士兵们
President Johnson awarded four Medals of Honor
颁发了四枚荣誉勋章
to men from each of the Armed Services.
美国必须向你表示感激  孩子
America owes you a debt of gratitude, son.
我知道你受伤了  你的伤在哪里
I understand you were wounded. Where were you hit?
在屁股上  长官
In the buttocks, sir.
那一定是道亮丽的风景线
That must be a sight.
我倒是想看看
I'd kind of like to see that.
我的天呐  孩子
God damn, son.
仪式后  妈妈回酒店休息
After that, Mama went to the hotel to lay down,
于是我出去参观我们国家的首都
so I went out for a walk to see our nation's capital.
希拉里  好了  我找到退伍军人了
Hilary, all right, I've got the vets,
你想让我带他们去哪里
what do you want me to do with them?
你这么晚来干什么
What are you doing here so late?
幸好妈妈在休息
It's a good thing Mama was resting,
因为街上到处都是
'cause the streets was awful crowded
参观雕像和纪念碑的人
with people looking at all the statues and monuments,
其中一些人大声喧哗  推来撞去
and some of them people were loud and pushy.
好了  跟我走  我们走
Okay, follow me! Come on. Let's move it out.
无论我走到哪里  我都得站队
Everywhere I went, I had to stand in line.
跟我走  我们走
Follow me, let's go!
跟上  快走
Come on. Let's go.
站在这里
Stand here.
你这么做真棒  真棒
You're a good man for doing this. Good!
好吧
Okay.
台上有个男人在演讲
There was this man giving a little talk.
不知为什么  他穿着美国国旗做的衬衫
And for some reason, he was wearing an American flag for a shirt.
现在  我要带一些士兵上来
Now, I'm gonna bring up some soldiers...
他还很喜欢说"操"这个字
And he liked to say the "F" word. A lot.
"操"这个  "操"那个
"F" this and "F" that.
而每一次他说"操"这个字
And every time he said the "F" word,
不知为什么  人们都会欢呼
people, for some reason, well, they'd cheer.
操他妈的这该死的战争
where to stick this fucking war!
来啊  兄弟  站到这里来
Come on, man, come up here, man.
上去  上去  就是你  上上上
Come on. Come on. Yeah, you! Come on. Move, move, move.
你可以的  站上来  就这样
You can do it. Just get up there. Go on. That's it.
跟我们讲讲战争吧
Tell us a little bit about the war, man.
让军队
回家
停止轰炸
越战吗
The war in Vietnam?
就是那该死的越战
The war in Viet-fucking-nam!
支持我们的美国兵  让他们回家
和平
Peace!
说啊  兄弟  快说
Come on, man, go!
-说啊  -和平
- Come on! - Peace!
关于越战  我只能说一件事
There was only one thing I could say about the war in Vietnam.
关于越战
There's only one thing I can say about
我只能说一件事
the war in Vietnam.
在越南
In Vietnam,
你的...
your...
你他妈在做什么...
What the hell are you...
我打死你  你这头该死的猪
I'll beat your head in, you goddamn oinker!
上帝啊  这些要怎么接
Jesus Christ, what'd they do with this?
我们听不见你说话
We can't hear you!
我们什么都听不见
We can't hear anything!
-这个  这个  给我那个  -大声点
- This one! This one! Give me that! - Turn it up!
大声说
Speak up!
接好了
That's it!
这就是我要说的
And that's all I have to say about that.
太对了  你说得很好
That's so right on, man. You said it all.
你叫什么
What's your name, man?
我叫弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
My name is Forrest. Forrest Gump.
弗里斯特·甘
Forrest Gump!
-阿甘  -阿甘
- Gump! - Gump!
弗里斯特  弗里斯特
Forrest! Forrest!
-珍妮  -弗里斯特
- Jenny! - Forrest!
那是我一生中最快乐的时刻
It was the happiest moment of my life.
珍妮和我又形影不离了
Jenny and me were just like peas and carrots again.
她带我四处参观
She showed me around,
甚至还把我介绍给她的一些新朋友
and even introduced me to some of her new friends.
把窗帘关上
Shut that blind, man.
你这个白人  离窗户远点
And get your white ass away from that window.
你不知道我们这里在打仗吗
Don't you know we in a war here?
他没事  他没事  他是我们的一员
Hey, man, he's cool. He's cool. He's one of us.
-我来跟你说说关于我们这个组织  -你到底去哪了
- Let me tell you about us. - Where the hell have you been?
我们的目的是保护我们的黑人领袖
Our purpose here is to protect our black leaders
免受警察的种族攻击
from the racial onslaught of the pig
那些警察想要虐待我们的黑人领袖
who wishes to brutalize our black leaders,
强奸我们的女人  摧毁我们的黑人社区
rape our women, and destroy our black communities.
反战者对美军的称呼
这个婴儿杀手是谁
Who's the baby killer?
是我跟你提过的那个好朋友  弗里斯特·甘
This is my good friend I told you about. This is Forrest Gump.
弗里斯特  这是韦斯利
Forrest, this is Wesley.
韦斯利和我一起住在伯克利
Wesley and I lived together in Berkeley,
他是学生民主协会伯克利分会的会长
and he's the president of the Berkeley chapter of SDS.
我再跟你说说其他的
Let me tell you something else.
我们是为了向所有
We are here to offer protection
需要我们帮助的人  提供保护和帮助
and help for all of those who need our help,
因为我们  黑豹党  反对越战
because we, the Black Panthers, are against the war in Vietnam.
没错  我们反对任何战争
Yes, we are against any war
那些战争中  黑人士兵被送往前线
where black soldiers are sent to the frontline
为一个憎恶他们的国家牺牲
to die for a country that hates them.
没错  我们反对任何黑人士兵参与的战争
Yes, we are against any war where black soldiers go to fight
当他们晚上睡觉时  在自己的社区
and come to be brutalized and killed in their own communities
被残害  被杀害
as they sleep in their beds at night.
没错  我们反对一切种族主义和帝国狗行为
Yes, we are against all these racist and imperial dog acts.
弗里斯特  住手  住手
Forrest! Quit it! Quit it!
弗里斯特
Forrest!
停手  停下来
Stop it! Stop it!
天呐
Oh, God...
我就不该带你到这里
I shouldn't have brought you here.
我早该知道这只会是些狗屁麻烦事
I should have known it was just gonna be some bullshit hassle.
他不该打你  珍妮
He should not be hitting you, Jenny.
走吧  弗里斯特
Come on, Forrest.
对不起我在你的黑豹党派对中途打架了
Sorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther party.
他不是有意做这种事的  他不是
He doesn't mean it when he does things like this. He doesn't.
我永远都不会伤害你  珍妮
I would never hurt you, Jenny.
我知道你不会  弗里斯特
I know you wouldn't, Forrest.
我想当你的男朋友
I wanted to be your boyfriend.
那身制服是场经历  弗里斯特
That uniform is a trip, Forrest.
你穿着很帅气  真的
You look handsome in it. You do.
-你猜怎么着  -什么
- You know what? - What?
我很高兴我们在国家首都相聚
I'm glad we were here together in our nation's capital.
我也是  弗里斯特
Me, too, Forrest.
珍妮和我散步一整晚  只是聊天
We walked around all night, Jenny and me, just talking.
她说了她所有的旅行
She told me about all the traveling she'd done.
以及她发现如何开拓自己的思维
And how she'd discovered ways to expand her mind
学会如何和谐生活
and learn how to live in harmony,
珍·哈露
那肯定是在西部的某个地方
which must be out west somewhere,
因为她一路去到了加州
'cause she made it all the way to California.
♪现在就试着去爱对方♪
♪Try to love one another right now♪
有人想去旧金山吗
Anybody want to go to San Francisco?
-我去  -好极了
- I'll go. - Far out.
对我们两个来说  这是非常特别的一晚
It was a very special night for the two of us.
我当时盼着那一夜永不结束
I didn't want it to end.
伯克利至华盛顿特区
我不想你离开  珍妮
I wish you wouldn't go, Jenny.
我必须离开  弗里斯特
I have to, Forrest.
珍妮
Jenny?
事态有些失控了
Things got a little out of hand.
就因为这场战争和那个满嘴胡话的混蛋约翰逊
It's just this war and that lying son of a bitch, Johnson!
我永远不会伤害你  你知道的
I would never hurt you, you know that.
你知道我是怎么想的吗
You know what I think?
我觉得你应该回阿拉巴马州的绿弓县
I think you should go home to Greenbow, Alabama!
弗里斯特  我们的生活截然不同
Forrest, we have very different lives, you know.
我希望你收下这个
I want you to have this.
弗里斯特  我不能要
Forrest, I can't keep this.
我能得到这个
I got it
完全是因为我照你说的做了
just by doing what you told me to do.
你为什么对我这么好
Why are you so good to me?
你是我的姑娘
You're my girl.
我永远都是你的姑娘
I'll always be your girl.
就那样  她走了  又从我的生命中消失
And just like that, she was gone, out of my life again.
那是一个人的一小步
That's one small step for man,
却是人类的一大步
one giant leap for mankind.
我以为我又要回越南了
I thought I was going back to Vietnam,
但他们却认定
but instead, they decided
让我对抗共产党的最好方式
the best way for me to fight the Communists
就是打乒乓球
was to play Ping-Pong.
所以  我加入了特别服务部队
So, I was in the Special Services,
在全国各地
traveling around the country
为所有受伤的退伍军人加油打气
cheering up all them wounded veterans
并教他们怎么打乒乓球
and showing them how to play Ping-Pong.
我打得太好了  以至于几年后
I was so good that some years later
军队决定让我加入全美乒乓球队
the Army decided that I should be on the All-American Ping-Pong team.
我们是近百万年来  大概可以这么说吧
We were the first Americans to visit the land of China
第一批踏上中国大陆的美国人
in like a million years, or something like that.
有人说世界和平就掌握在我们手中
Somebody said world peace was in our hands,
但我只是打了乒乓球而已
but all I did was play Ping-Pong.
当我回家时  我成了全美名人
When I got home, I was a national celebrity.
比袋鼠船长还有名
Famouser even than Captain Kangaroo.
他来了  弗里斯特·甘
Here he is, Forrest Gump, right here.
阿甘先生  请坐
Mr. Gump, have a seat.
弗里斯特·甘  这是约翰·列侬
Forrest Gump, John Lennon.
-欢迎回家  -你刚结束了令人震撼的中国行
- Welcome home. - You had quite a trip.
你能告诉我们  中国是什么样子的吗
Can you tell us, what was China like?
在中国  人们几乎一无所有
In the land of China, people hardly got nothing at all.
没有财产吗
No possessions?
在中国  人们从不去教堂
And in China, they never go to church.
也没有宗教信仰吗
No religion, too?
-难以想象  -只要你肯尝试  其实很容易  迪克
- Hard to imagine. - Well, it's easy if you try, Dick.
几年后  那位来自英国的帅小伙
Some years later, that nice young man from England
在回家看他儿子的路上
was on his way home to see his little boy
当他正在签名时
and was signing some autographs,
无缘无故地  有人射杀了他
and for no particular reason at all, somebody shot him.
演播室观众入口
他们给你颁发了国会荣誉勋章
They gave you the Congressional Medal of Honor.
那是丹中尉
Now, that's Lieutenant Dan.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan!
他们给你颁发了国会荣誉勋章
They gave you the Congressional Medal of Honor!
没错  长官  是给我颁发了
Yes, sir, they surely did.
他们竟然给你  一个低能儿  一个白痴
They gave you, an imbecile, a moron
一个在电视上当着全国人民的面
who goes on television and makes a fool out of himself
自出洋相的人
in front of the whole damn country,
颁发了国会荣誉勋章
the Congressional Medal of Honor.
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
那真是太好了
Well, then, that's just perfect!
好吧  我对此只想说一句话
Yeah, well, I just got one thing to say to that.
上帝保佑美国
God damn bless America.
天呐
Oh, God!
-天呐  -丹中尉
- Oh, God! - Lieutenant Dan!
丹中尉说他住在一个旅馆里
Lieutenant Dan said he was living in a hotel.
因为他没有腿
And because he didn't have no legs,
所以他大部分时间都在锻炼手臂
he spent most of his time exercising his arms.
右转  右转
Take a right. Take a right.
拜托  快点啊
Come on, already!
你在纽约做什么  丹中尉
What do you do here in New York, Lieutenant Dan?
我靠政府救济生活
I'm living off the government tit.
吸干它
Sucking it dry!
你瞎了吗
Are you blind?
-我走路呢  -快走开
- I'm walking here! - Get out of the way!
走吧  快  走走走
Get out! Come on, go! Go! Go!
我和丹上尉一起庆祝了节日
I stayed with Lieutenant Dan and celebrated the holidays.
大家这一年很棒  回家吧  上帝祝福你们
You have a great year. Hurry home and God bless you.
你找到耶稣了吗  阿甘
Have you found Jesus yet, Gump?
我都不知道我应该要找祂啊  长官
I didn't know I was supposed to be looking for him, sir.
退伍军人中心的那帮瘸子
That's all these cripples, down at the VA,
整天就说这个
that's all they ever talk about.
耶稣这  耶稣那
Jesus this and Jesus that.
我有没有找到耶稣
Have I found Jesus?
他们甚至找了个牧师来和我谈话
They even had a priest come and talk to me.
他说上帝在倾听  但我得自救
He said God is listening, but I have to help myself.
说什么如果我诚心接受耶稣
How if I accept Jesus into my heart,
我将和他在天堂并肩行走
I'll get to walk beside him in the kingdom of heaven.
你听见我说的话了吗
Did you hear what I said?
和他在天堂并肩行走
Walk beside him in the kingdom of heaven.
给老子滚蛋去吧
Well, kiss my crippled ass.
上帝在倾听  一派胡言
God is listening? What a crock of shit.
我会上天堂的  丹上尉
I'm going to heaven, Lieutenant Dan.
那在你去之前  不如先去一趟街角
Before you go, why don't you get your ass down to the corner
-再买瓶酒回来  -遵命  长官
- and get us another bottle of Ripple. - Yes, sir.
我们现在大约在纽约45街的
We are at approximately 45th Street
阿斯特广场一号
in New York City at One Astor Plaza.
这里是阿斯特酒店旧址
This is the site of the old Astor Hotel.
拜尤拉巴特里到底有什么
What the hell is in Bayou La Batre?
-捕虾船  -捕虾船
- Shrimping boats. - Shrimping boats?
谁他妈在乎捕虾船啊
Who gives a shit about shrimping boats?
等我有钱  就给自己买一艘捕虾船
I gotta buy me one of them shrimping boats, soon as I have some money.
我在越南和巴巴说好了
I made me a promise to Bubba in Vietnam
等战争结束  我们就合伙捕虾
that as soon as the war was over, we'd go in partners.
他做捕虾船的船长
He'd be the captain of the shrimping boat
我当他的大副
and I'd be his first mate.
但现在他死了  我得担起船长的重任
But now that he's dead, that means I gotta be the captain.
-捕虾船的船长  -没错  长官
- A shrimp boat captain. - Yes, sir.
一言既出  驷马难追  丹上尉
A promise is a promise, Lieutenant Dan.
快听听啊
Now hear this!
二等兵阿甘要当捕虾船的船长了
Private Gump here is gonna be a shrimp boat captain.
我跟你说  吉利根[典出剧集《吉利根岛》]
Well, I tell you what, Gilligan,
等你当上捕虾船船长的那天
the day that you are a shrimp boat captain,
-我来当你的大副  -好的
- I will come and be your first mate. - Okay.
如果你真能当上捕虾船船长
If you're ever a shrimp boat captain,
那天我就当宇航员了
that's the day I'm an astronaut.
丹尼  你在抱怨什么呢
Danny, what are you complaining about?
-你在干什么  亲爱的  -轮椅帅哥
- What are you doing, hon? - Mr. Hot Wheels.
你的朋友叫什么
Who's your friend?
我叫弗里斯特  弗里斯特·甘
My name is Forrest, Forrest Gump.
这是狡猾卡拉和长腿丽诺
This is Cunning Carla and Long-Limbs Lenore.
你去哪儿了  甜心派
So, where you been, baby cakes, huh?
最近都没见到你
Haven't seen you around lately.
你圣诞节时真该来这里的
You know, you should have been here for Christmas,
因为汤米请所有人喝了一轮酒
'cause Tommy bought a round on the house
还给大家火鸡三明治
and gave everybody a turkey sandwich.
好吧  我有伴儿了
Well, well, I had company.
我们刚刚就在那  时代广场
We was just there. That's at Times Square.
谁能不爱新年呢  你可以从头来过
Don't you just love New Year's? You get to start all over.
-嘿  丽诺  -每个人都有第二次机会
- Hey, Lenore... - Everybody gets a second chance.
说来有趣  在那欢乐的气氛之中
It's funny, but in the middle of all that fun,
我开始想念珍妮
I began to think about Jenny,
想着她会如何在加州度过新年夜
wondering how she was spending her New Year's night out in California.
八  七  六  五
Eight, seven, six, five,
四  三  二  一
four, three, two, one!
新年快乐
Happy New Year!
新年快乐  丹上尉
Happy New Year, Lieutenant Dan!
你怎么回事  是不是傻
What are you, stupid or something?
你有什么毛病
What's your problem?
他有什么毛病
What's his problem?
你是打仗把鸡巴打没了还是怎么着
Did you lose your pecker in the war or something?
怎么  你朋友是不是傻
What, is your friend stupid or something?
你刚说什么
What did you say?
我说  你朋友是不是傻
I said, is your friend stupid or something?
不准说他傻
Don't call him stupid!
-嘿  你别推她  -你闭嘴
- Hey, don't you push her! - You shut up!
-永远不准骂他傻  -怎么了  宝贝
- Don't you ever call him stupid! - What's the matter, baby?
-你为什么发这么大火  -给我滚出去
- Why are you so upset? - Just get the hell out of here.
-蠢玩意儿  -拿好你们的衣服
- Stupid damn... - Get your goddamn clothes...
你就该上瑞普利的《信不信由你》节目
You belong in Ripley's Believe It Or Not!
专门报道阐述奇闻怪象的节目
有漫画书  广播  电视等多种形式
-给我滚出去  -你就该去马戏团作为怪胎表演
- Get the hell out of here! - You should be in a sideshow!
赶紧  滚出去
Go on! Get out of here!
走吧  丽诺  我们没必要受这气
Come on, Lenore. We don't need this shit!
滚出去
Get out of here!
-你个智障  -废物  你个怪胎
- You retard. - Loser. You freak.
不  别碰我
No, no.
很抱歉毁了你的新年前夜派对  丹上尉
I'm sorry I ruined your New Year's Eve party, Lieutenant Dan.
她身上一股烟味
She tasted like cigarettes.
我猜丹上尉觉得
I guess Lieutenant Dan figured
有些事你无法改变
there's some things you just can't change.
他不想让别人叫他瘸子
He didn't want to be called crippled,
就像我不想让别人说我傻
just like I didn't want to be called stupid.
新年快乐  阿甘
Happy New Year, Gump.
美国国家乒乓队
The US Ping-Pong team
今日在总统办公室里与尼克松总统见面
met with President Nixon today at an Oval Office ceremony...
你猜怎么着  几个月后
And wouldn't you know it? A few months later,
他们邀请我和乒乓球队去白宫
they invited me and the Ping-Pong team to visit the White House.
所以我又去了
So, I went, again.
而且我又见到了美国总统
And I met the President of the United States, again.
弗里斯特·甘
美国国家乒乓球队
1971年最佳球员
只是这次  他们没给我们安排豪华酒店
Only, this time, they didn't get us rooms in a real fancy hotel.
你在首都玩的开心吗  年轻人
So, are you enjoying yourself in our nation's capital, young man?
-是的  长官  -你们住在哪里
- Yes, sir. - Well, where are you staying?
-埃伯特酒店  -不不  这可不行
- It's called the Hotel Ebbott. - Oh, no, no, no, no.
我知道一个更好的酒店  崭新  非常现代
I know of a much nicer hotel. It's brand-new, very modern.
我会让我的手下给你安排
I'll have my people take care of it for you.
安保部  弗兰克·威尔斯
Security, Frank Wills.
你好  先生  你最好派一位维修人员
Yeah, sir, you might want to send a maintenance man
到对面的办公室看看
over to that office across the way.
灯灭了
The lights are off,
他们肯定是在找保险丝盒什么的
and they must be looking for a fuse box or something,
因为他们在用手电筒  闪的我睡不着
'cause them flashlights, they're keeping me awake.
好的  先生  我去检查一下
Okay, sir. I'll check it out.
-谢谢  -不客气
- Thank you. - No problem.
-晚安  -晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
水门饭店
因此  我将于
Therefore, I shall resign
明天中午辞去总统一职
the presidency effective at noon tomorrow.
副总统福特
Vice President Ford
将于同一时间宣誓就职
will be sworn in as president at that hour in this office.
我尤记得在第二任期开始时
As I recall the high hopes for America
对美国给予的厚望...
with which we began this second term...
阿甘中士
Sergeant Gump.
-在  长官  -稍息
- Yes, sir! - As you were.
这是你的退伍文件
I have your discharge papers.
你的服役结束了  孩子
Your service is up, son.
这意思是我不能再打乒乓球了吗
Does this mean I can't play Ping-Pong no more?
不能再为军队打了
For the Army it does.
就那样
And just like that,
我在美国军队的服役生涯结束了
my service in the United States Army was over.
于是我回家了
So, I went home.
我回来了  妈妈
I'm home, Mama.
我知道  我知道
I know, I know.
-露易丝  他回来了  -当我回家时
- Louise, he's here. - Now, when I got home,
我浑然不知  但妈妈接待了许多客人
I had no idea, but Mama had had all sorts of visitors.
我们接待了许多客人  弗里斯特
We've had all sorts of visitors, Forrest.
大家都想让你用他们的乒乓器材
Everybody wants you to use their Ping-Pong stuff.
有个人甚至留下一张2.5万美元的支票
One man even left a check for $25,000
只要你愿意说你喜欢用他们的乒乓球拍
if you'd be agreeable to saying you liked using their paddle.
但妈妈  我只喜欢用我自己的拍子
Oh, but, Mama, I only like using my own paddle.
-你好  露易丝小姐  -你好  弗里斯特
- Hi, Miss Louise. - Hey, Forrest.
我知道  我知道
I know that. I know that.
但这可是2.5万美元  弗里斯特
But it's $25,000, Forrest.
我想也许你可以握着试试
I thought maybe you could hold it for a while,
看会不会慢慢喜欢上
see if it grows on you.
-你气色不错  弗里斯特  -这点我妈倒是没说错
- Oh, you look good, Forrest. - That Mama, she sure was right.
-你气色很好  -事情的发展真是出人意料
- You look real good. - It's funny how things work out.
我在家没待多久
I didn't stay home for long,
因为我曾承诺过巴巴
because I'd made a promise to Bubba,
而我总是努力信守承诺
and I always try to keep my promise.
于是我去了拜尤拉巴特里
So, I went on down to Bayou La Batre
去见巴巴的家人  相互认识
to meet Bubba's family and make their introduction.
你是疯子  还是单纯的傻子
Are you crazy, or just plain stupid?
只有做傻事的才是傻子  布鲁太太
Stupid is as stupid does, Mrs. Blue.
也许吧
I guess.
当然  我也去祭奠了一下巴巴
And, of course, I paid my respect to Bubba himself.
本杰明·巴福德·布鲁
我们的巴巴
嗨  巴巴  是我  弗里斯特·甘
Hey, Bubba, it's me, Forrest Gump.
我记得你说过的一切  而且我都想好了
I remember everything you said, and I got it all figured out.
我这里有我赚的24562美元47美分
I'm taking the $24,562 and 47 cents that I got...
其实是花剩下的  我理了发  买了新西服
Or, that's left after a new hair cut and a new suit,
带妈妈去吃了一顿豪华大餐
and I took Mama out to a real fancy dinner,
还买了车票和三瓶汽水
and I bought a bus ticket and three Dr. Peppers.
跟我说说
Tell me something.
你是不是个傻子
Are you stupid or something?
只有做傻事的才是傻子  先生
Stupid is as stupid does, sir.
其实这笔钱是我做广告赚的  我宣传说
Well, that's what's left after me saying,
"当我代表全美乒乓球队去中国打比赛时
"When I was in China on the All-America Ping-Pong team,
我最爱的乒乓球拍
"I just loved playing Ping-Pong
是我那「巧又轻」牌的球拍"
with my Flex-O-Light Ping-Pong paddle,"
尽管大家都知道这不是真的
which everybody knows isn't true,
但妈妈说这是个小小的善意谎言
but Mama says it's just a little white lie
不会伤害到任何人
so it wouldn't hurt nobody.
总之  我把钱都用来买汽油  绳索和新网
So, anyway, I'm putting all that on gas, ropes and new nets
以及一艘全新的捕虾船
and a brand-new shrimping boat.
巴巴教过我他所知的一切关于捕虾的知识
Now, Bubba had told me everything he knew about shrimping,
但你知道我发现了什么吗
but you know what I found out?
捕虾太难了
Shrimping is tough.
我只捕到5只虾
I only caught five.
再来几只  你就能给自己做道鸡尾酒鲜虾了
A couple more, you could have yourself a cocktail.
你想过给这船起名吗
You ever think about naming this old boat?
有船无名可不吉利
It's bad luck to have a boat without a name.
我之前从没给船起过名
I'd never named a boat before,
但我只能想到一个名字
but there was only one I could think of,
这世上最美的名字
the most beautiful name in the wide world.
珍妮
我已经好久没有珍妮的消息
Now, I hadn't heard from Jenny in a long while,
但我经常想她
but I thought about her a lot,
我希望无论她现在在做什么  都能让她快乐
and I hoped that whatever she was doing made her happy.
我无时不刻不想着珍妮
I thought about Jenny all the time.
丹上尉  你来这里干什么
Lieutenant Dan, what are you doing here?
想来试试我的海洋腿[在船上平稳行走的能力]
Well, thought I'd try out my sea legs.
但你没有腿  丹上尉
But you ain't got no legs, Lieutenant Dan.
是的  我知道
Yes, I know that.
你给我写信了  蠢货
You wrote me a letter, you idiot.
瞧瞧  弗里斯特·甘船长
Well, well. Captain Forrest Gump.
我必须亲自来看看
I had to see this for myself.
我说过  如果你当上了捕虾船船长
And I told you if you were ever a shrimp boat captain
我就来做你的大副  我来了
that I'd be your first mate. Well, here I am.
-我是个信守承诺的男人  -好棒
- I am a man of my word. - Okay.
但你别妄想我会叫你"长官"
But don't you be thinking that i'm going to be calling you "sir."
不会的  长官
No, sir.
那是我的船
That's my boat.
我有种预感  如果我们往正东方行驶
I have a feeling if we head due east,
就会捕到虾
we'll find some shrimp,
所以左转
so take a left.
-左转  -哪边
- Take a left! - Which way?
那边  它们在那里
Over there! They're over there!
-把舵扶稳了  左转  -好的
- Get on the wheel and take a left! - Okay.
阿甘  你在干什么  左转  左左左
Gump, what are you doing? Take a left! Left!
我们肯定能在那里捕捞到虾  小子
That's where we're going to find those shrimp, my boy!
我们将在那里捕捞到虾
That's where we'll find them.
-还是没虾  丹上尉  -好吧  我错了
- Still no shrimp, Lieutenant Dan. - Okay, so I was wrong.
我们要怎么做才能找到虾呢
How are we going to find them?
要不你去祷告  把虾子盼来
Well, maybe you should just pray for shrimp.
于是我每周日都会去教堂做礼拜
So, I went to church every Sunday.
有时候丹中尉也会去
Sometimes Lieutenant Dan came, too,
不过祷告都是我一个人在做
though I think he left the praying up to me.
没有虾
No shrimp.
你拜的那个上帝怎么还不显灵
Where the hell's this God of yours?
丹中尉这么说真的挺好笑的
It's funny Lieutenant Dan said that,
因为他话音刚落  上帝就显灵了
'cause right then, God showed up.
-别想沉掉这艘船  -当时我害怕极了
- You'll never sink this boat! - Now, me, I was scared,
但是丹中尉像发疯了一样
but Lieutenant Dan, he was mad.
来啊
Come on!
这也叫暴风雨
You call this a storm?
放马过来啊  王八蛋
Come on, you son of a bitch!
我们两个是时候决一死战了
It's time for a showdown! You and me!
我就在这  来打败我啊
I'm right here! Come and get me!
你休想弄沉这艘船
You'll never sink this boat!
飓风卡门于昨日席卷该地区
Hurricane Carmen came through here yesterday,
几乎摧毁了沿途的一切
destroying nearly everything in its path.
而说到沿海的其他小镇
And as in other towns up and down the coast,
拜尤拉巴特里的整个虾行业
Bayou La Batre's entire shrimping industry
因飓风卡门而遭到重创  损失惨重
has fallen victim to Carmen and has been left in utter ruin.
一位记者采访了当地官员后
Speaking with local officials, this reporter has learned,
得知仅有一艘捕虾船幸免于难
in fact, only one shrimping boat actually survived the storm.
露易丝  快看  是弗里斯特
Louise. Louise, there's Forrest.
在那之后  捕虾变得轻而易举
After that, shrimping was easy.
因为大家还是需要虾来做鸡尾酒鲜虾
Since people still needed them shrimps for shrimp cocktails
还有烧烤什么的
and barbecues and all,
再加上只剩下了我们这么一艘船
and we were the only boat left standing,
他们就只能靠巴巴甘虾业了
Bubba-Gump Shrimp's what they got.
我们之后又采购了许多船只
We got a whole bunch of boats,
12艘珍妮号  还有个老旧的大仓库
12 Jennys, a big old warehouse.
我们还专门定做了印有"巴巴甘"品牌名的帽子
We even have hats that say "Bubba-Gump" on them.
巴巴甘虾业  家喻户晓
Bubba-Gump Shrimp. It's a household name.
等等  小伙子
Hold on there, boy.
你是在告诉我
Are you telling me
你就是巴巴甘虾业的老板吗
you're the owner of the Bubba-Gump Shrimp Corporation?
没错  我们挣的钱比大卫·克洛科特还多
Yes, sir. We got more money than Davy Crockett.
天呐  我这辈子没少听人吹牛
Boy, I heard some whoppers in my time,
但你这绝对是最扯的
but that tops them all.
我们竟然和百万富翁坐一张凳子上了
We was sitting next to a millionaire.
我觉得你的故事非常精彩
Well, I thought it was a very lovely story,
你讲得很生动  激情澎湃的
and you tell it so well, with such enthusiasm.
你想看看丹中尉长什么样吗
Would you like to see what Lieutenant Dan looks like?
好啊
Well, yes, I would.
那就是他
That's him right there.
财富
我跟你说啊  丹中尉这个人...
And let me tell you something about Lieutenant Dan...
弗里斯特
Forrest,
我从未感谢你救了我一命
I never thanked you for saving my life.
他的确从未开口谢过我
He never actually said so,
但我觉得他已经和上帝重归于好了
but I think he made his peace with God.
这是17天以来的第二次
For the second time in 17 days,
福特总统今天逃过了一起潜在的暗杀行动
President Ford escaped possible assassination today.
总部呼叫珍妮一号
Base to Jenny 1.
这里是珍妮一号  请说  玛格
Jenny 1. Go, Margo.
有人来电找弗里斯特
Forrest has a phone call.
是吗  跟那个人说回头再打过来
Yeah, well, you'll have to tell them to call him back.
-他现在没空  -他妈妈病了
- He is indisposed at the moment. - His mama's sick.
-妈妈在哪儿  -在楼上
- Where's Mama? - She's upstairs.
嗨  弗里斯特
Hi, Forrest.
-我明天再来  -好的
- I'll see you tomorrow. - All right.
现在能站得笔直的了啊  小伙子
We sure got you straightened out, didn't we, boy?
你怎么了  妈妈
What's the matter, Mama?
我快要死了  弗里斯特
I'm dying, Forrest.
快进来  坐这里
Come on in, sit down over here.
你为什么快要死了  妈妈
Why are you dying, Mama?
我的时候到了
It's my time.
就是时候到了
It's just my time.
好了
Now,
不要害怕  亲爱的
don't you be afraid, sweetheart.
死亡只是人生的一部分
Death is just a part of life,
人终有一死
something we're all destined to do.
我以前不知道  但我注定要做你的妈妈
I didn't know it, but I was destined to be your mama.
-我也尽了全力  -你做得很好  妈妈
- I did the best I could. - You did good, Mama.
我相信一个人的命运该由自己创造
I happen to believe you make your own destiny.
你要好好利用上帝赋予你的一切
You have to do the best with what God gave you.
我的命运是什么  妈妈
What's my destiny, Mama?
这就得由你自己慢慢领悟了
You're going to have to figure that out for yourself.
生活就像一盒巧克力  弗里斯特
Life is a box of chocolates, Forrest.
你永远不知道你将得到什么
You never know what you're going to get.
妈妈总是有办法把事情解释得
Mama always had a way of explaining things
让我也能听懂
so I could understand them.
我会想你的  弗里斯特
I will miss you, Forrest.
她患了癌症  然后在一个礼拜二去世
She had got the cancer and died on a Tuesday.
我给她买了一顶碎花帽子
I bought her a new hat with little flowers on it.
关于这事  我要说的就这么多
And that's all I have to say about that.
你不是说你在等7路公交车吗
Didn't you say you were waiting for the number seven bus?
没关系  下一班很快就到
There'll be another one along shortly.
因为我当过橄榄球明星  战争英雄
Now, because I had been a football star, and a war hero,
全国名人  捕虾船船长
and a national celebrity, and a shrimping boat captain,
以及大学生
and a college graduate,
阿拉巴马州绿弓县的市议员们
the city fathers of Greenbow, Alabama
一同商量后  决定给我一份好工作
decided to get together and offered me a fine job.
于是  我没再回去给丹中尉工作了
So, I never went back to work for Lieutenant Dan,
不过他确实在好好帮我理财
though he did take care of my Bubba-Gump money.
他给我投资了一家水果公司
He got me invested in some kind of fruit company.
后来  他打电话告诉我说
And so then, I got a call from him saying
我们再也不用操心没钱用了
we don't have to worry about money no more,
苹果电脑公司
我回答说  "挺好的  少个烦心事"
and I said, "That's good. One less thing."
我妈妈常说一个人不需要太多财富
Now, Mama said there's only so much fortune a man really needs,
多出来的只是为了显摆
and the rest is just for showing off.
所以我就把一大笔钱捐给了正方福音教堂
So, I gave a whole bunch of it to the Foursquare gospel church,
阿甘医疗中心
我还捐了一大笔钱给拜尤拉巴特里渔业医院
and I gave a whole bunch to the Bayou La Batre Fishing Hospital.
虽然巴巴不在了
And even though Bubba was dead
丹中尉说我这么做简直是疯了
and Lieutenant Dan said I was nuts,
我把巴巴的股份转给了他妈妈
I gave Bubba's mama Bubba's share.
你猜怎么着
You know what?
她再也不用给别人家当佣人了
She didn't have to work in nobody's kitchen no more.
好香啊
That smells wonderful.
因为我有用不完的钱  而且非常喜欢这一行
And 'cause I was a gazillionaire and I liked doing it so much,
我都是免费除草的
I cut that grass for free.
但每当夜晚来临  无所事事
But at night time when there was nothing to do
家里空荡荡的时候
and the house was all empty,
我总会想起珍妮
I'd always think of Jenny.
后来有一天  她回来了
And then, she was there.
你好  弗里斯特
Hello, Forrest.
你好  珍妮
Hello, Jenny.
珍妮回来后  跟我住在一起
Jenny came back and stayed with me.
也有可能是她无处可去了吧
Maybe it was because she had nowhere else to go,
也有可能是她筋疲力尽了
or maybe it was because she was so tired,
因为她睡了好久好久
'cause she went to bed and slept and slept,
就跟好几年没睡过觉似的
like she hadn't slept in years.
她能回家我真的很开心
It was wonderful having her home.
我们每天都会出门散步
Every day we'd take a walk
我就像树上的猴子一样喋喋不休
and I'd jabber on like a monkey in a tree,
她静静地听我说着关于打乒乓球  捕虾
and she'd listen about Ping-Ponging, and shrimping,
还有妈妈去天堂的各种经历
and Mama making a trip up to heaven.
都是我一个人在说
I did all the talking.
珍妮大多数时候都一言不发
Jenny most of the time was real quiet.
你怎么能这样对我
How could you do this?
有时我觉得  石头都不够她砸的
Sometimes I guess there just aren't enough rocks.
我从没搞懂过她为什么回来
I never really knew why she came back,
不过我也不在乎
but I didn't care.
一切就像回到了从前
It was like olden times.
我们又变得形影不离了
We was like peas and carrots again.
我每天都会摘下鲜花
Every day, I'd pick pretty flowers
装点她的房间
and put them in her room for her,
她也送了我一件
and she gave me the best gift
全世界最好的礼物
anyone could ever get in the wide world.
-一双新鞋  -这是专业跑步鞋
- New shoes. - They make them just for running.
她还教我怎么跳舞
And she even showed me how to dance.
珍妮和我  就像一家人一样
And, well, we was like family, Jenny and me.
那是我人生中最幸福的时光
And it was the happiest time in my life.
今年的独立日
...and this Fourth is witnessing
举办了全国最为盛大的焰火晚会
one of the largest fireworks displays in the nation's...
-你看完了吗  -就在纽约港
- You done watching it? - ...here in New York Harbor...
我要上床睡觉了
I'm going to bed.
自由女神像...
The Statue of Liberty...
嫁给我好吗
Will you marry me?
我会是个好丈夫的  珍妮
I'd make a good husband, Jenny.
你一定是  弗里斯特
You would, Forrest.
但你不愿意嫁给我
But you won't marry me.
你不会想娶我的
You don't want to marry me.
你为什么不爱我  珍妮
Why don't you love me, Jenny?
我虽然不够聪明
I'm not a smart man,
但我知道什么是爱
but I know what love is.
珍妮
Jenny.
弗里斯特  我是爱你的
Forrest, I do love you.
你这是要逃去哪儿
Where are you running off to?
我这不是要逃
I'm not running.
那天  没有缘由地
That day, for no particular reason,
我决定出去跑一圈
I decided to go for a little run.
于是我跑到了路的尽头
So, I ran to the end of the road,
当我跑到那里时
and when I got there,
我想着要不跑到镇子的另一头去吧
I thought maybe I'd run to the end of town.
卡特总统由于中暑
President Carter, suffering from heat exhaustion,
跌入了...
fell into the arms of...
当我跑到那里后
And when I got there,
我就想着干脆横穿绿弓县吧
I thought maybe I'd just run across Greenbow County.
然后我想既然已经跑了这么远
And I figured since I'd run this far,
不如就跑遍整个阿拉巴马州吧
maybe I'd just run across the great state of Alabama.
欢迎来到密西西比州
我真这么做了
And that's what I did.
我跑步横穿了阿拉巴马州
I ran clear across Alabama.
没有缘由  我就一直向前跑
For no particular reason, I just kept on going.
我一直跑到了大海边
I ran clear to the ocean.
圣莫尼卡
当我到达那里时  心想都跑这么远了
And when I got there, I figured since I'd gone this far,
不如调个头继续跑下去
might as well turn around and just keep on going.
当我抵达另一个大洋时
And when I got to another ocean,
心想既然都到这了
I figured since I'd gone this far,
不如转过身  再继续跑下去
I might as well just turn back and keep right on going.
我跑累了就睡  饿了就吃
When I got tired, I slept. When I got hungry, I ate.
要方便的时候  你懂的
When I had to go, you know...
我就去方便
I went.
所以你一直都在跑
And so, you just ran.
是的
Yeah.
一路我想了很多有关妈妈  巴巴和丹中尉的事
I'd think a lot about Mama and Bubba and Lieutenant Dan.
不过我主要还是在想珍妮
But most of all, I thought about Jenny.
我老是会想起她
I thought about her a lot.
在两年多的时间里
For more than two years now,
一位名叫弗里斯特·甘的男子
a man named Forrest Gump,
阿拉巴马州绿弓县的一位园丁
a gardener from Greenbow, Alabama,
除了停下来睡觉之外
stopping only to sleep,
跑遍了整个美国
has been running across America.
请看查尔斯·库珀带来的报道
Charles Cooper brings us this report.
在第四次跑遍全美的旅行中
For the fourth time on his journey across America,
弗里斯特·甘
Forrest Gump,
阿拉巴马州绿弓县的一位园丁
the gardener from Greenbow, Alabama,
将于今日再次穿越密西西比河
is about to cross the Mississippi River again today.
-我的天呐  弗里斯特  -先生  你为什么要跑步呢
- I'll be damned. Forrest? - Sir, why are you running?
为什么要跑步
Why are you running?
是为了宣扬世界和平吗
Are you doing this for world peace?
还是为了那些流浪汉
Are you doing this for the homeless?
是为了妇女权利而跑吗
Are you running for women's rights?
还是为了环保
Or for the environment?
还是动物保护
Or for animals?
他们就是不敢相信
They just couldn't believe
会有人不为任何原因跑遍全国
that somebody would do all that running for no particular reason.
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
我就是想跑
I just felt like running.
是你  没想到真的是你
It's you. I can't believe it's really you.
但现在  不知怎么的
Now, for some reason,
别人似乎能够理解我的行为了
what I was doing seemed to make sense to people.
我感觉  就像脑袋突然开窍了一样
I mean, it was like an alarm went off in my head, you know?
我说  「这家伙是个积极振作的人」
I said, "Here's a guy that's got his act together.
「这家伙参透了一切」
"Here's somebody who's got it all figured out.
「这家伙知晓人生答案」
"Here's somebody who has the answer."
无论你去哪里  我都跟着你  甘先生
I'll follow you anywhere, Mr. Gump.
于是就有人跟着我了
So, I got company.
之后  有了更多的人
And after that, I got more company.
再然后  更多的人加入了
And then, even more people joined in.
后来有人跟我说  这能给人希望
Somebody later told me it gave people hope.
不过  我对此倒是不是很明白
Now... Now, I don't know anything about that,
但其中有些人问我能不能帮助他们
but some of those people asked me if I could help them out.
嘿  老兄  不知道能不能请你帮个忙
Hey, man, hey, listen, I was wondering if you might help me, huh?
听着  我是生产车尾贴的
Listen, I'm in the bumper sticker business
我一直在努力想出一条好标语
and I've been trying to think up a good slogan.
因为你如此激励人心
And since you have been such a big inspiration
带动了这里的很多人
to the people around here,
我想着  也许你能帮我想一个标语
I thought you might be able to help me jump into...
天呐  你刚刚跑过了一堆狗屎
Whoa, man! You just ran through a big pile of dog shit!
-这很正常  -什么  狗屎吗
- It happens. - What, shit?
有时候
Sometimes.
多年后  我听说那家伙
And some years later, I heard that that fellow
还真的想到了一条出色的车尾贴标语
did come up with a bumper sticker slogan,
还因此赚了很多钱
and he made a lot of money off of it.
屎属正常
还有一次  跑步的时候
Another time, I was running along,
有人说他的T恤生意赔光了钱
somebody who had lost all his money in the T-shirt business,
他想把我的脸印在T恤上
he wanted to put my face on a T-shirt,
但他画画不好  又没有相机
but he couldn't draw that well, and he didn't have a camera.
给  用这个  反正也没人喜欢这个颜色
Here, use this one. Nobody likes that color anyway.
祝你愉快
Have a nice day.
很多年后
Well, some years later,
我发现那个人为T恤想到了好的创意图案
I found out that that man did come up with an idea for a T-shirt.
他因此赚了很多钱
He made a lot of money off of it.
总之  就像我说的
Anyway, like I was saying,
有很多人陪着我同行
I had a lot of company.
我妈妈生前常说
My mama always said,
「要想向前走  就得先放下过去」
"You got to put the past behind you before you can move on."
我觉得这就是我跑步的意义
And I think that's what my running was all about.
我跑了三年  两个月
I had run for three years, two months,
加14天16小时
14 days and 16 hours.
安静  安静  他要说话了
Quiet. Quiet. He's going to say something.
我累了
I'm pretty tired.
我要回家了
Think I'll go home now.
那我们该怎么办
Now what are we supposed to do?
就那样
And just like that,
我的跑步生涯结束了
my running days was over.
于是我回到了阿拉巴马的家里
So, I went home to Alabama.
就在刚才  下午2:25
Moments ago, at 2:25 P.M.,
里根总统正要...
as President Reagan was leaving the...
五六次枪击
...five or six gunshots
嫌疑刺客身份未知
were fired by an unknown would-be assassin.
总统胸部中枪  刺客...
The President was shot in the chest, and the assailant...
我帮你收了邮件
I picked up the mail.
有一天  非常突然地
And one day, out of the blue clear sky,
我收到了来自珍妮的信
I got a letter from Jenny,
她问我能不能去萨凡纳看望她
wondering if I could come down to Savannah and see her,
所以我就来了
and that's what I'm doing here.
她在电视上看到我跑步
She saw me on TV, running.
我应该坐9号公交车去里士满街
I'm supposed to go on the number nine bus to Richmond Street
下车  走一个街区
and get off and go one block
左转去亨利街1947号  4号公寓
left to 1947 Henry Street, Apartment 4.
你可不用坐公交车
Why, you don't need to take a bus.
往那个方向走五六个街区就能到亨利街
Henry Street is just five or six blocks down that way.
-那边吗  -就是那边
- Down that way? - Down that way.
很高兴和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
希望你一切顺利
I hope everything works out for you!
弗里斯特
Forrest!
你好吗
How you doing?
请进  请进
Come in, come in!
我收到了你的信
I got your letter.
我还在想你有没有收到呢
I was wondering about that.
这是你的家吗
Is this your house?
是的  有点乱  我刚下班
Yeah. It's messy right now. I just got off work.
挺好的
It's nice.
你这里还有空调呢
You got air conditioning.
-谢谢  -我吃掉了一些
- Thank you. - I ate some.
我留了一本你的剪报和其他材料
I kept a scrapbook of your clippings and everything.
跑步者的世界
这是你
There you are.
这个  你跑步的时候
And this, I got you running.
夜店舞女表示
弗里斯特·甘让我做他的秘密情人
我不认识她
我跑了好远
I ran a long way,
跑了很久
for a long time.
这里
And there...
听着  弗里斯特  我不知道该怎么说
Listen, Forrest, I don't know how to say this.
我想为我对你的所作所为道歉
I just I want to apologize for anything that I ever did to you,
因为我迷失了很久
'cause I was messed up for a long time, and...
你回来啦
Hey, you.
-这位是阿拉巴马来的老朋友  -你好
- This is an old friend from Alabama. - How do you do?
听着  下周我换了班
Listen, next week my schedule changes,
所以我就可以...但是谢谢了
so I'll be able to... But thanks...
没事  我要走了  珍  我把车靠着别人的车停了
No problem. Got to go, Jen, I'm double-parked.
-好  谢谢  -再见
- Okay. Thanks. - Bye.
这是我的好朋友  甘先生
This is my very good friend, Mr. Gump.
跟他打个招呼好吗
Can you say hi to him?
-你好  甘先生  -你好
- Hello, Mr. Gump. - Hello.
-我能去看电视了吗  -好  但要小声
- Can I go watch TV now? - Yes, you can. Just keep it low.
-你当妈妈了  珍妮  -我当妈妈了
- You're a mama, Jenny. - I'm a mama.
他的名字叫弗里斯特
His name's Forrest.
和我一样
Like me.
我用他父亲的名字给他起名的
I named him after his daddy.
他父亲也叫弗里斯特吗
He got a daddy named Forrest, too?
你就是他父亲  弗里斯特
You're his daddy, Forrest.
弗里斯特  看着我  看着我  弗里斯特
Forrest, look at me. Look at me, Forrest.
你什么都不需要做  好吗
There's nothing you need to do, okay?
你没有做错任何事
You didn't do anything wrong.
好吗
Okay?
他很漂亮  不是吗
Isn't he beautiful?
他是我见过的最漂亮的孩子
He's the most beautiful thing I've ever seen.
但是
But...
他聪明吗  还是...
Is he smart, or...
他很聪明
He's very smart.
他是他们班上最聪明的一个
He's one of the smartest in his class.
没事的  去和他说说话吧
Yeah, it's okay. Go talk to him.
-你在看什么  -伯特和厄尼
- What are you watching? - Bert and Ernie.
弗里斯特  我病了
Forrest, I'm sick.
怎么了  你感冒了吗
What, do you have a cough due to a cold?
我感染上了一种病毒
I have some kind of virus,
医生们  他们不知道是什么病毒
and the doctors don't... They don't know what it is,
他们也没办法治疗
and there isn't anything they can do about it.
你可以和我回家
You could come home with me.
珍妮  你和小弗里斯特
Jenny, you and little Forrest
可以和我一起住在绿弓县
could come stay at my house in Greenbow.
你要是病了  我可以照顾你
I'll take care of you if you're sick.
你愿意娶我吗  弗里斯特
Would you marry me, Forrest?
好啊
Okay.
请入座
Please take your seats.
弗里斯特  该开始了
Forrest? It's time to start.
你的领带
Your tie.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
你好  弗里斯特
Hello, Forrest.
你换上新腿了  新腿
You got new legs. New legs!
是的  我有新腿了  专门定制的
Yeah. I got new legs. Custom-made.
钛合金的
Titanium alloy.
是用来造航空飞船的材料
It's what they use on the space shuttle.
魔法腿
Magic legs.
这是我的未婚妻  苏珊
This is my fiancee, Susan.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
你好  弗里斯特
Hi, Forrest.
丹中尉  这是我的珍妮
Lieutenant Dan, this is my Jenny.
你好
Hi.
很高兴终于见到你了
It's nice to meet you finally.
弗里斯特  你愿意接受珍妮做你的妻子吗
Do you, Forrest, take Jenny to be your wife?
珍妮  你愿意接受弗里斯特做你的丈夫吗
Do you, Jenny, take Forrest to be your husband?
我宣布你们结为夫妻
And so I pronounce you man and wife.
嘿  弗里斯特
Hey, Forrest.
在越南的时候你怕吗
Were you scared in Vietnam?
是的  我...
Yes. Well, I...
我不知道
I don't know.
有时候雨停得足够久  就能看到星星
Sometimes it would stop raining long enough for the stars to come out.
那种时候还好
And then it was nice.
就像太阳要睡觉前的海湾
It was like just before the sun goes to bed down on the bayou.
海面总有无数光芒闪烁
There was always a million sparkles on the water.
就像天池  特别清澈  珍妮
Like that mountain lake. It was so clear, Jenny,
看起来就像有两个天空  一个扣在另一个上面
it looked like there were two skies, one on top of the other.
还有在沙漠  当太阳升起时
And then, in the desert, when the sun comes up,
我都无法分辨  天与地的交接处是在哪里
I couldn't tell where heaven stopped and the earth began.
真的太美了
It was so beautiful.
真希望当时我能和你一起欣赏这些美景
I wish I could've been there with you.
你在的
You were.
我爱你
I love you.
你在一个周六的清晨去世了
You died on a Saturday morning.
我把你安葬在了我们的树下
And I had you placed here under our tree.
我把你父亲的房子推平了
And I had that house of your father's bulldozed to the ground.
妈妈
Mama
总说死亡是人生的一部分
always said that dying was a part of life.
珍妮·甘
我真希望不是这样
I sure wish it wasn't.
小弗里斯特过得很好
Little Forrest is doing just fine.
但是
But...
他很快又要开始上学了
About to start school again soon,
我每天都给他做早餐  午餐  晚餐
and I make his breakfast, lunch and dinner every day.
我每天确保他梳头  刷牙
I make sure he combs his hair and brushes his teeth every day.
教他怎么打乒乓球
Teaching him how to play Ping-Pong.
好的
Okay.
他很棒
He's really good.
弗里斯特  你来发球
Forrest, you go.
我们经常钓鱼
We fish a lot.
每天晚上我们都读书  他好聪明  珍妮
And every night, we read a book. He's so smart, Jenny.
你一定会为他骄傲的
You'd be so proud of him.
我为他骄傲
I am.
他给你写了一封信
He wrote you a letter.
他说我不能看
And he says I can't read it.
我不能看  所以就留给你了
I'm not supposed to, so I'll just leave it here for you.
给妈妈
珍妮
Jenny,
我不知道妈妈说的对不对
I don't know if Mama was right,
或者丹中尉说的对不对
or if it's Lieutenant Dan.
我不知道
I don't know
是不是每个人都有宿命
if we each have a destiny,
或者我们只是像风一般飘摇
or if we're all just floating around accidental-like on a breeze.
但我觉得
But I think
也许二者皆有吧
maybe it's both.
也许两种情况是同时发生的
Maybe both is happening at the same time.
但我很想你  珍妮
But I miss you, Jenny.
如果你有什么需要  我就在不远处
If there's anything you need, I won't be far away.
你的校车来了
Here's your bus.
好了
Okay.
我知道这本书
I know this.
我要拿去班上做展示演讲  因为...
I'm gonna show that for show-and-tell because
奶奶曾给你念过这本书
Grandma used to read it to you.
我最喜欢的书
My favorite book.
车来了
Here we are.
好了
Okay.
去吧
Here you go.
嘿  弗里斯特  不要...
Hey, Forrest, don't...
-我想告诉你  我爱你  -我也爱你  爸爸
- I wanted to tell you, I love you. - I love you, too, Daddy.
你回来的时候我就在这里等你
I'll be right here when you get back.
你知道这车是去学校的  对吧
You understand this is the bus to school, now, don't you?
当然  你是多洛希·哈里斯
Of course, and you are Dorothy Harris,
我是弗里斯特·甘
and I'm Forrest Gump.